<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Petrus Cunæus of the common-wealth of the Hebrews. Translated by C.B.</title>
            <author>Cunaeus, Petrus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7584</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1311_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209172</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868062</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868062</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169754</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169754)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 175:E1311[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Petrus Cunæus of the common-wealth of the Hebrews. Translated by C.B.</title>
                  <author>Cunaeus, Petrus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 166, [16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.W. for William Lee, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Turks Head in Fleet-street over against Fetter-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a half-title.</note>
                  <note>Original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 28 1652"; the '3' in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jews --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jews --  Social conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169754:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>PETRUS CUNAEUS</hi> OF THE COMMON-WEALTH OF THE <hi>HEBREWS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated by <hi>C. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Nec omnia, nec nihil.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. W.</hi> for <hi>William Lee,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop at the Sign of the Turks Head in Fleet-ſtreet over againſt Fetter-Lane. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:169754:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169754:2"/>
            <head>THE AVTHOR'S PREFACE, TO The States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Weſtfriſia.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt illuſtrious Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Offer to your view a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the moſt holy, and the moſt exemplary in the
<pb facs="tcp:169754:3"/>whole World. The Riſe and Advance whereof, it well becomes you perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to underſtand, becauſe it had not any mortall man for its Author and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but the immortall God; that God, whoſe pure veneration and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, You have underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and do maintain. Here you ſhall ſee, what it was that conteined the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews ſo long in an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent way of life; what rais'd up their courage, cheriſhed their concord, bridled their deſires. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that people had
<pb facs="tcp:169754:3"/>Rules of Government, excelling the precepts of all wiſe men that ever were; Which Rules, we have ſhewed, may in good part be collected out of the holy Bible. Only, of their Military Diſcipline very little is deliver'd to our memory: Yet muſt every one, that conſiders their victories and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements, confeſs, that the Hebrews, for milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vertue, were inferiour to none. For, in the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of baniſhed men, when they were come out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> where they had long
<pb facs="tcp:169754:4"/>ſate, after a tedious march up and down in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts of <hi>Arabia</hi> for the ſpace of forty years, they encountred with mighty and valiant Nations, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd them, and poſſeſſed their Country, where they built new Towns, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to God a magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Temple. In this moſt happy ſoil, where their valour had planted them, their mutuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord made them grow to admiration. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of all provided for the ſafety of all; and the Cities, which were many,
<pb facs="tcp:169754:4"/>did not every one aim at their own dominion, but all uſed their beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to defend the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Liberty. That the Government might bee compleat and uniform, they had the ſame Laws, Magiſtrates, Senators, Judges; and the ſame weights, meaſures, mony. Wherefore, all <hi>Paleſtin</hi> might be accounted as one City, but only that all the Inhabitants were not ſhut up within the ſame Walls. Such a Community and Conformity there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them all. Yet, by
<pb facs="tcp:169754:5"/>the Law, there was one City Privileg'd above all the reſt; not, to have dominion over the reſt, but that all, even the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt dwellers, ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very year thrice hold their Religious meetings in it. A thing ſo far from bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any difference among them, that it was the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt bond of union. Thus did the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> every one being multiplyed marvellouſly into the greatneſs of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, overſpread a very great and fertile Country. The force of enemies, the
<pb facs="tcp:169754:5"/>Tempeſts of Wars, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the like evils nothing prevail'd againſt them. They alwaies roſe higher by their overthrows, were enriched by their loſſes, and the keeneſs of their enemies ſword put the more courage in them. For a long time the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews continued in this ſtate: till at laſt, after <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> death, having at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the height of proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, a great alteration happened. A certain man, <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> all whoſe hopes conſiſted in the diſcord of
<pb facs="tcp:169754:6"/>the people, ſtird up ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among them, and drawing to his party ten whole Tribes, conſtituted a kind of Common-wealth a part to himſelf, the head whereof was <hi>Samaria.</hi> And now there was no longer one, but two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths. That of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> or the ten Tribes, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted but a little while, being conquered, and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into eternall exile. The other of the Jews, whoſe imperiall City was <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> although, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the times of <hi>Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> the Emperour, it was
<pb facs="tcp:169754:6"/>not wholly ruined, yet the power of it was ſo enfee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that it could ſeldom bear up againſt the enemy. Certainly, none of all this had come to paſs, had not they fallen to pieces by their own diſſentions, who whilſt they held to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and kept their force united, were victorious o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo many Nations. The diſcords of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple give the greateſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the enemy. This was the cauſe of the Hebrews ruin, and the ſame hath deſtroyed the moſt flouriſhing Kingdoms
<pb facs="tcp:169754:7"/>other Nations. Pleaſe you to return into the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of all former times, you ſhall find ſcarce any other thing to have given a check to the moſt high and moſt mighty States. Fortune (though envious to ſuch as proſper) ſeldom aſſiſteth any people to the deſtruction of another, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the people firſt create trouble to themſelves at home, knowing neither how to moderate their vices, nor govern their own forces. It is clear, That Politic Nation the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans (<hi>who</hi> as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith,
<pb facs="tcp:169754:7"/>
               <hi>by defending their confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates made themſelves Maſters of all the world</hi>) underſtood exceeding well, how the moſt eaſy way to ſubdue confederate peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, was by their domeſtic troubles and diſſentions. Thus, while they aided the oppreſſed party, or became Arbitrators of the difference, they brought all things into their own power, and <hi>where they had made a waſte, they called it peace.</hi> The Achaians were once terrible to all their Neighbours, by means of a confederacy, wherein
<pb facs="tcp:169754:8"/>upon fair conditions the Cities of <hi>Peloponneſus</hi> were united; Their Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth was of an excellent frame, and very like to yours (moſt illuſtrious Lords) ſtrengthned by their united powers, and invincible. How often did that Lordly people of <hi>Rome,</hi> knowing <hi>Greece</hi> was inexpugnable ſo long as confederated, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by art and cunning to diſſolve that union? The Proconſul <hi>Gallus</hi> was put upon the buſineſs: and, when he found no ſucceſs, the Spartans, by a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous
<pb facs="tcp:169754:8"/>device were added to the ligue, but upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall terms, to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall cauſe of difference amongſt them. This af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward undid the Achai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. The Annals are full of ſuch examples, but here is no place to make a long relation. <hi>Rome,</hi> the Lady of all Nations, born for the ruin of the world (as <hi>Mithridates</hi> ſaid) groaning under the peoples diſcord, and Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors faction, at laſt gave up her liberty, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her proud neck to the yoke of <hi>Caeſar.</hi> But, to
<pb facs="tcp:169754:9"/>return to the Hebrews, I ſhall mention that in the laſt place, which is the chief of all. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd breach, after <hi>Salomons</hi> death, had been probably made up again in a ſhort time, but that the ambitious Author of it, <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> by changing the old true Religion into a vain and ſenſeleſs ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, obſtructed the way of concord, and by a ſmooth oration having obtruded upon the ten Tribes his new invention, made them very prone to take armes, not ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:169754:9"/>now for their Eſtates and Liberty, as for their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars and Idols. Theſe things, and many more of this ſort, we have diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of in this Treatiſe: and we thought it not unfit to ſee the light. You that are the Fathers of your Country, have alwaies had this truth in mind: <hi>That by concord a ſmall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is raiſed, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt is by diſcord over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</hi> Your own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience confirms you in it, ſince by divine favour, and your own vertue, and the conduct of your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible
<pb facs="tcp:169754:10"/>Leader, your Common-wealth, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degrees, is at laſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to that height, that your enemies can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of nothing, but your greatneſs. As I pray for the perpetuity of this U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, whereby you are ſo happily advanced; ſo, when I conſider your wiſdom, which hath ſhined forth in the greateſt Tryals, I am very confident, the ſame will laſt, as all good men would have it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main for ever. Yet, I confeſs, we are not ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, but that ſometimes
<pb facs="tcp:169754:10"/>we reflect our thoughts upon the examples of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages. Many of your ſubjects are already gone into ſides, and oppoſe each other with contrary opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, ſince here ſprung up amongſt them ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable controverſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout myſteries of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not underſtood by the moſt part of the people. The multitude are carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeverall wayes by their affections, and every day the flame encreaſes. Your ſelves underſtand (moſt illuſtrious Lords) how
<pb facs="tcp:169754:11"/>much it concerns you to apply (and you do apply) ſeaſonable remedies to this diſtemper, leſt your flouriſhing affairs receive ſome detriment by this inteſtine malady, more pernicious than forein War, than Famine, than Peſtilence. 'Tis vain for me to ſpeak more, when I can propoſe nothing to you out of my deepeſt conſideration, which is not obvious to your own judgement. Only my Petition to your Highneſs is, that you would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe
<pb facs="tcp:169754:11"/>an intentive eye to this Common-wealth, which I have here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, the moſt ſacred, and the beſt that ever was. Here you ſhall find ſome things which Kings and Princes and the Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of publick affairs may ſelect and lay up for their uſe. And truly I was the more eaſily moved to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer theſe to you, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men ſitting in your Senate, whoſe learning is ſo exact, that, if I have brought any thing for the
<pb facs="tcp:169754:12"/>illuſtration of antiquity and of the beſt Authors, they are able to paſs a right judgement on it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 17. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>for</hi> two, <hi>r.</hi> too. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>for</hi> their, <hi>r.</hi> there. <hi>p.</hi> 122. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>for</hi> myſtery, <hi>r.</hi> miniſtry. <hi>p.</hi> 137. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>for</hi> carried, <hi>r.</hi> carved. <hi>p.</hi> 150. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>for</hi> good, <hi>r.</hi> God. <hi>p.</hi> 136. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>for Suſa,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Suſac. p.</hi> 137. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>r. Salmanaſſar.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169754:12"/>
            <head>OF THE COMMON-WEALTH Of The <hi>HEBREWS.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Inſtitution of the</hi> Hebrew <hi>Commonwealth. Legiſlation. The Vain-glory of the</hi> Grecians. <hi>The ſeven Precepts of the Sons of</hi> Noah. <hi>The deſign of</hi> Moſes <hi>in his Laws and Ordinances.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this work we ſhall not be over curious in our method, nor make any accurate ſearch after mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, but lay hold upon ſuch
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169754:13"/>things as freely and familiarly offer themſelves to our conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and as they come into our mind, ſet down our diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon them all. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> was founded by that excellent Man of God, <hi>Moſes,</hi> the firſt Man that undertook a buſineſs of the greateſt conſequence in the World: For, amongſt all the Actions of old, which Fame hath left upon record, this in my judgement is the moſt noble, the conſtitution of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, and the ordering of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Societies by good Laws. Nothing is more acceptable to God, the Almighty Governour of this Univerſe. As the honour hereof is very great; ſo, many Nations have laid claim unto it. The <hi>Grecians,</hi> among the reſt of the benefits, wherewith
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169754:13"/>they boaſt themſelves to have obliged other Nations, put Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlation in the Head of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. <hi>Lycurgus, Draco, Solon,</hi> and other Antients, are names they glory in. Their Glory is but vain: For, all the Brags of this blown and arrogant Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are ſilenc'd by the <hi>Jew, Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius Joſephus,</hi> whoſe Apology extant againſt <hi>Apion</hi> (an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and a Man ſo famous for his eloquence that he was called <hi>Cymbalum Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di</hi>) is full of admirable learning.
<note place="margin">Plin. praf.</note> There he ſhews, that the Greek Legiſlators, compar'd to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> are but of yeſterday: for, at what time their Father <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> liv'd, they knew not the name of Laws, nor is it extant in all his Poems; Onely, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had in their mouth certain common ſayings and ſentences,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169754:14"/>whereby they were govern'd; to ſupply the defects whereof, the unwritten Edicts of Princes were upon occaſion added. The truth is, which <hi>Flavius</hi> hath well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, <hi>Moſes, Homer</hi>'s <hi>Senior</hi> by many ages, is the onely Man to whom this honour apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, which ſo many afterward were ambitious of. He was the firſt writer and publiſher of Laws, teaching the people, what was right or wrong, juſt or unjuſt, and by what Decrees that Common-wealth was to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, which the moſt high God had commanded to ſettle in <hi>Paleſtin.</hi> Before the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> no written Laws were known in the World: for, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though mankind liv'd not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together without Laws before, yet were not thoſe Laws conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated and kept in any publick
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169754:14"/>records or monuments. Of this ſort were thoſe ſeven Precepts which the <hi>Talmudiſts</hi> ſay were given to the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning certain Rules of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs neceſſary for the life of Man. Wherefore they were of ſo large extent, that whoſoever knew them not, thoſe the <hi>Iſrael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> were commanded to deſtroy by War, and deprive them of all Communion with mankind; And juſtly: For, they that had received no Law, ſeemed worſe than beaſts; and (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath divinely ſpoken) <hi>injuſtice ſtrengthened with Arms and Power is moſt cruell and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable.</hi> Now the Arms wherewith nature hath ſurni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Man, are Reaſon and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; things enabling him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly for miſchief, if they be not reſtrained and regulated
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169754:15"/>by Laws. But let us return to <hi>Moſes.</hi> In his inſtitution of that Common-wealth, the moſt holy upon earth, he aſſigned the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power to God; and when others find other names (as the matter requires) calling the Government Monarchy, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligarchy, or Democracy, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived none of theſe appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſuitable to the nature of ſo great an Empire: Wherefore he ordained ſuch a kind of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which <hi>Flavius</hi> ſaith may very ſignificantly be ſtil'd <hi>Theocracy,</hi> that is, a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth whoſe Ruler and Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent is God alone; For, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed all affairs were managed by divine judgement and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. And of this he gave an evident demonſtration, in as much as although he ſaw all matters depending upon him,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169754:15"/>and had all the people at his devotion, yet upon ſo fair an invitation he ſought no power, no wealth, no honour for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. A thing, whereby he ſhew'd himſelf more than Man: For, in all Men there is implanted a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Rule, a deſire inveterate, more flagrant and eager than all other affections whatſoever: Which, I believe, <hi>Moſes</hi> had never been able to expectorate and extinguiſh, had he not ſeen God himſelf preſent and preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in all affairs; with whom, to ſeek a Partnerſhip in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, had been an extreme degree of madneſs. Moreover, He ordered that the Magiſtrates ſhould not be Lords and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, but Keepers of the Laws and Miniſters. An excellent Conſtitution: for, ſeeing even the beſt Men are ſometimes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169754:16"/>tranſported by paſſion, the Laws alone are they that alwaies ſpeak with all perſons in one and the ſame impartiall voice; Which I conceive to be the meaning of that fine ſaying of <hi>Ariſtotle, The Law is a Mind without Affection.</hi> Laſtly, we conſider that which is not the leaſt of all, the eternall ſtability of <hi>Moſes</hi> Laws: whereto to adde, where from to take ought away, was a moſt high offence. So that, neither old Laws were aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, nor new brought in, but the obſervation of the firſt was exacted of all with rigour, even in the declination of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. Which was not ſo in other Common wealths, being both founded and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by Law-making: for, as many of the Rulers, affecting to bring in ſomewhat of their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169754:16"/>own, have changed things before well ordered; ſo, many good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by deſuetude, more (which is worſe) aboliſhed by contempt, gave ſecurity to vices. This di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity we could never wonder at; ſeeing the Laws of other Nations, Inventions of humane Wit, are enforced only by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties that by time, or through the ſloath of Governours, loſe their terrour: but the Jewiſh Ordinances, being the Decrees of the eternall God not weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned either by continuance of time, or ſoftneſs of the Judges, they remain ſtill the ſame; and when the Ax and Scourge are no longer feared Mens minds are nevertheleſs kept in awe by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:169754:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The prudence of the Lawgiver concerning Aſſignation of Lands. That they ought not to have been the firſt Seizer's. The</hi> Agrarian <hi>Law, and its ineſtimable Uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. The Redemption of lands. The benefit of the Jubily, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FLavius Joſephus</hi> often cites <hi>Hecataeus</hi> of <hi>Abdera,</hi> an Author of great Faith and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, one that waited upon <hi>Alexander</hi> the great in his Wars; Many Countries he view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, abounding with all kind of fruits, but admired none ſo much as <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> Of this he wrote a ſingular Book, out of which <hi>Ioſephus</hi> recites many things in favour of the Jews. To our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he ſaith the Jews inhabited
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169754:17"/>a very good Country, and moſt fruitful, conteining three hundred thouſand Acres; a ſeat, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into as moſt fit for them, the divine goodneſs tranſplanted the <hi>Hebrews</hi> out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> For, as formerly they had ſpent their lives in tillage of the ground, and feeding of Cattel; ſo here in a bounteous ſoil they might ſtill inrich themſelves, and proſper by the ſame profeſſion. So ſoon as the holy people had by force of Arms poſſeſſed themſelves of the promiſed Land, the chief Captain <hi>Ioſua</hi> preſently put in execution the commands of <hi>Moſes.</hi> The whole Country he divided into twelve portions, and gave it to be inhabited by the twelve Tribes. Then, he numbred the families in every Tribe, and according to the number of perſons gave to every
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169754:18"/>family a certain proportion of Lands, and preſcrib'd their bounds. By this means, all were equally provided for; which is the prime care of good Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in every Common-wealth; a care, that the moſt Politick Nations, the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> in after-times were not unmindfull of when they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried forth their Colonies. Had every one made that his own, upon which he firſt ſet his foot, quarels and commotions among the people muſt needs have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed: for ſo it uſually comes to paſs; whilſt every one ſeeks to get and appropriate to himſelf what was common, Peace is loſt. Moreover. <hi>Moſes,</hi> as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a wiſe Man, not only to order things at preſent, but for the future ages too, brought in a certain Law providing that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169754:18"/>the wealth of ſome might not tend to the oppreſſion of the reſt; nor the people change their courſe, and turn their minds from their innocent labours to any new and ſtrange employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This was the <hi>Agrarian</hi> Law; a Law, whereby all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſors of Land were kept from transferring the full right and dominion of it unto any other perſon, by ſale or other contract whatſoever: For, both they that on conſtraint of poverty had ſold their Land, had a right granted them to redeem it at any time; and they that did not redeem it, receiv'd it freely again, by this Law, at the ſolemn feaſt of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bily. There is a great writer, <hi>Rabbi Moſes Ben Maimon,</hi> he that in his divine work en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily collected all the Talmudicall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169754:19"/>doctrine except the trifles, an Author above our higheſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, the only Man of that Nation, who had the good fortune to underſtand what it is to write ſeriouſly and to the purpoſe; We ſhall often make uſe of his Authority, and now it will help us out in the matter we have in Hand. He is much upon the benefit of the Jubily, conſiſting (ſaith he) herein, that all Lands returned to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Lords, although they had paſſed through the Hands of a hundred buyers. Neither are excepted, by this moſt learned writer, the Lands which came to any one by donation. Theſe could no more than other be retained from the firſt poſſeſſor. It is a point of the Talmudicall Law, and I make no queſtion but 'tis very right. The ſame
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169754:19"/>
                  <hi>Rabbin</hi> from the ſame fountain declares, that Redemption was permitted only to ſuch as were recovered from their poverry, and enabled by ſome gain or commodity that had befallen them. The reaſon's plain; for, to borrow money, or to ſell one piece of Land to redeem ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was to fruſtrate the Law, that appointed the unable, and their Heirs, to wait for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of Jubily. Yet might the Kinſmen of the neceſſitous, in the mean time, buy off for their money, what the poor owner, without borrowing, could not. Theſe Jubily-ſolemnities retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned every fiftieth year, beginning at the ſeaventh month <hi>Tiſri.</hi> No other time brought with it ſo much publick joy: for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the repoſſeſſion of Lands that had been alienated, liberty
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169754:20"/>was given unto all ſervants. Yet was nothing done before the tenth of that month, a holy Faſt and day of Expiation. The nine preceding dayes were all ſpent in publick mirth and feaſting, like the Roman <hi>Saturnalia.</hi> Hear how <hi>Maimonides</hi> relates it. <hi>From the beginning of the year, to the day of Expiations, neither were the ſervants diſmiſt, nor did they ſerve their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. What then? The ſervants did eat and drink and make merry, and every one of them ſet a Crown upon his Head. After, when the day of Expiations was come, the Senators of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrin ſounded with their trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and forthwith the ſervants went away free, and the old Lords took a repoſſeſſion of their Lands.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169754:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Again of the</hi> Agrarian <hi>Law. The danger of two ample poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. The Roman Common-wealth.</hi> Stolo<hi>'s Law. How the Hebrews maintained them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The Legiſlators provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Divine Laws of Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culture and Paſturage.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt we have more to ſay of the utility intended by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> in the <hi>Agrarian</hi> Law. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, it was of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Common-wealth, as before we noted, that the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice of a few ſhould not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the poſſeſſions diſtributed with ſo fair equality. It is not unuſuall with rich men to thruſt the poor out of his inheritance, and deprive him of neceſſaries, whilſt they enlarge their own
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169754:21"/>eſtate ſuperfluouſly. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth often a change of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: For, the truth is, That Common-wealth is full of enemies, wherein the people, many of them having loſt their antient poſſeſſions, with reſtleſs deſires aſpire to a better fortune. Theſe men weary of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſtudy alterations, and ſtay no longer, than they needs muſt, in an unpleaſing condition. Time was, when at <hi>Rome</hi> the principall men (drawing all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves, inſomuch that one Citizen poſſeſſed Land e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for three hundred) were confined by <hi>Stolo</hi>'s Law to five hundred Acres a Man. But that good order, by fraud, was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broken. <hi>Stolo</hi> himſelf was the firſt to violate his own Sanction, and was found guilty for hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a thouſand Acres, making
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169754:21"/>uſe of his Sons name, whom to that end he had emancipated. And after, by other arts, many others eluded the ſentence of the Law, themſelves poſſeſſing what was purchaſed by their Agents. This abuſe being perceiv'd by the wiſe <hi>Lelius,</hi> friend to <hi>Scipio A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricanus,</hi> he endeavour'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforce the Law, but overborn by the adverſe faction, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent contention and diſcord, he deſiſted. So the way was open for licence, and poſſeſſions were enlarged out of all meaſure; till at laſt all <hi>Italy</hi> and the next provinces fell into a few Hands, as their proper patrimony: whereof, it were very eaſy to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege teſtimonies, but here is needleſs. We touched alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon of the <hi>Agrarian</hi> Law, namely, that <hi>Moſes</hi> would not have the people languiſh
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169754:22"/>and loſe their vertue by want of exerciſe. The moſt eminent of all their Anceſtors having led a paſtorall life, and been good Husbands in the Field, their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity could not be better ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from the vices and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities that follow idleneſs, than by being obliged to the ſame employments: which are not only the means of getting riches, but were uſed by the beſt Men even from the beginning of the World. Indeed, thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try employments would ſoon have been deſerted, had the Law permitted every one to purchaſe as much as he would, and lay Field to Field; Whereby it comes to paſs, that the Lords of ſo much Land diſdain to perform thoſe honeſt labours with their own Hands, but commit the buſineſs of Husbandry to others;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169754:22"/>ſuch as are, for the moſt part, ſtrangers hired, or ſervants bought with money. The inferiour peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, having no Heart to beſtow their labour on Land that is not their own, get out of the Fields into the Cities, and their immure themſelves, and are corrupted with an idle kind of life, ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome ſoft and illiberall Art. Verily, after that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Senators, and thoſe but few, engroſſed to themſelves the Fields which formerly belong'd to many, not the Citizens alone, but all free men neglected and forgot the art of tillage. The Country that had once ſeen ſuch brave and gallant men as <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Fabricius, Cato,</hi> was now fild with the noiſe of chained labourers and bondmen. The magnanimous of-ſpring of <hi>Romulus</hi> (as <hi>Varro</hi> complains)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169754:23"/>
                  <hi>did no longer exerciſe themſelves in the Corn-Fields and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards, but in the Circ and Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> For, they had now thrown away the Hook and Plow, who of old (ſaith he) had ſo divided the year, <hi>that every ninth day only they viſited the City; all the other dayes they attended their Country-affairs.</hi> Thus did they decline from their Anceſtors ways, which while they obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, they teaped a double bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; their Fields did abound with fruits, and their minds with vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. For prevention of the many publick evils that ariſe from the fore-mentioned neglect, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> a Man excellent both in divine and humane wiſdom provident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decreed the privileges of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and eſtabliſhed the Law of Jubily: A Law, that had not the leaſt ſhadow of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169754:23"/>nor conteined any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodity at all to the buyers of Land; for, in the ſale, an eye was ever caſt upon the Jubily, &amp; with reſpect unto the nearneſs or diſtance of it, the price did ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther riſe or fal. This is that,
<note place="margin">Lev. 25.14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> which is at large ſet down in <hi>Leviticus</hi> in theſe words: <hi>If thou ſell ought unto thy Neighbour, or buyeſt ought of thy Neighbours Hand, ye ſhall not oppreſs (or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent) one another: According to the number of years after the Jubily, thou ſhalt buy of thy Neighbour, and according to the number of years of the fruits he ſhall ſell unto thee: According to the multitude of years thou ſhalt increaſe the price thereof; and according to the fewneſs of years thou ſhalt diminiſh the price of it: for according to the number of the years ſhall he ſell
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169754:24"/>unto thee: Ye ſhall not therefore op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs (or deceive) one another.</hi> Now, if the Seller deſired to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem his Lands, before the Jubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it was alſo with great equity ordained, that he ſhould render back the price, only retaining ſo much of the money, as the buyer had receiv'd in profits. By this means, Reſtitution of Lands was made without any damage at all to either party; and Agriculture, their old honeſt employment, kept up in eſteem and practice amongſt all the people. What the nature and condition of that people was, to whom <hi>Moſes</hi> gave his Ordinances, cannot be doubted: for, among ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Laws which he made, as a great number concern Juſtice and Religion, ſo the reſt which pertain to their eſtates and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of profit, run all upon rules of Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169754:24"/>How carefully are the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple taught, when to give reſt to their Land, and to intermit their ſeeding? what they muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve at Harveſt and Vintage? What years it was allowed to gather fruit of the Vine? Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with what ſeverity are they forbidden to ſow mingled ſeed in the ſame ground; to mix divers kinds of Animals in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; or put them together under one Yoke? The reſt, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the breed of Cattle, Firſt Fruits, and Tenths, are almoſt infinite. They are handled at full in the <hi>Talmud:</hi> where they take up the ſixt part of the whole, or more. <hi>Maimonides</hi> hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended all in his Book, that he cals <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wherein are admirable ſecrets.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:169754:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>In what ſtreight every ſeventh year brought the Jews. The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit granted to this Nation by</hi> Alexander <hi>the Great, for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain prophecy. The Jews had little commerce with other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The Grecians ignorant of their affairs.</hi> Ariſtotles <hi>opinion of the Jews. Who are the beſt Common-wealths men. Of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SUch were the Laws given to the Hebrews: all whoſe wealth lay in the Fields. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the encreaſe whereof, they were in penury or abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance? Hence it was, that as oft as forein Kings impoſed tribute on them, every ſeventh year brought them into ſo great a ſtreight, that they were hardly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169754:25"/>able to raiſe the ſum. For their Law would not permit them to till the ground that year, and to gather in the fruits thereof, which yeelded all their money. <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving learned at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> out of <hi>Daniels</hi> Book, that a Grecian ſhould overthrow the Perſian Empire, glad with the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, bad the Jews ask of him ſome royall favour. They an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, no greater benefit could be done them, than the remiſſion of the ſeventh years tribute. It was granted. The Samaritans, when they ſaid much for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to obtein the ſame indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, were not heard. But, of all that can be ſaid in this kind, nothing is more luculent than that which
<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Apol. ad v. Ap.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Flavius</hi> gives in anſwer to <hi>Apion,</hi> in behalf of his Country-men: <hi>Neither do
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169754:26"/>we live near the Sea, nor delight in trading; nor have we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any commerce with other Nations: but our Cities are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from the Sea, and we our ſelves ſeated in a fruitfull Land, which we make more fruitfull by good Husbandry.</hi> Indeed, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſeverall Nations are ſo aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated by Trade, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of all Countries are tranſported and may ſeem na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall to every one, the Jews alone conteined themſelves within the bounds of their own Land, not applying themſelves unto negotiation. For they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not the Sea, nor viſited other people, nor were viſited by others. Whence it came to paſs, that the Grecians and others have delivered many fabulous reports concerning them. For very few had certain intelligence
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169754:26"/>of their affairs. <hi>Hecataeus</hi> is the only man that hath written truth; The reſt have related what they had by fame and hear-ſay; Which, how unſafe it is in all Hiſtory, appears by <hi>Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rus,</hi> a famous Author of old, who ſaid, <hi>Iberia,</hi> which he never ſaw, was one Citie: a ridiculous errour; for 'twas not a City, but a great and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous part of the Weſtern World. It is a marvellous ignorant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in <hi>Clearchus,</hi> that the Jews were propagated from the wiſe men of <hi>India,</hi> but had changed their name: the Philoſophers of <hi>India</hi> being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Callans,</hi> and in <hi>Cava Syria</hi> Jews. I am aſhamed, ſo great a man ſhould make ſuch a poor conjecture. But that which the ſame <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> there addes, as it is not incredible to us, ſo is it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169754:27"/>very glorious for that holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He ſaith, when he was in <hi>Aſia,</hi> there came unto him a certain Jew, a man of ſo much learning and ſcience, that in compariſon of him all the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians that were preſent, ſeemed to be but Blocks. Herein he hath made ſome amends for that, he had imprudently rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted concerning their Originall: which he had been better to have omitted, as a thing unknown to a ſtranger. And truly to me <hi>Flavius</hi> ſeems to glory in the Jews obſcurity, when he ſaith, They live in mediterranean pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Merchants and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers have no acceſs unto them. For ſo, they long kept their manners uncorrupted, and none of thoſe exotick things pertaining to luxury and riot was impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whereby moſt potent nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169754:27"/>are undone. The reſt of his words are ſuch, that <hi>Flavius,</hi> you may ſay, is proud of his Country: <hi>We dwell in a fertile Land, and in the culture of it we ſpend our Labour:</hi> as if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be greater or better. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> recites ſome Edicts, framed by moſt antient Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, coming very nigh unto the Moſaicall. <hi>Oxylus,</hi> King of the <hi>Elians,</hi> prohibited Lands to be mortgaged for mony; and the <hi>Locrians</hi> were not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſell the Inheritances of their Fathers. Which Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were (as the greateſt Author of naturall wiſdom noteth) to this purpoſe, that the people might not deſert the culture of their Fields. Wherefore he ſo often iterates it in his Politicks, that the beſt Common-wealth is, where the people live upon Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169754:28"/>and Paſture. He gives the reaſon: <hi>Becauſe they govern themſelves and their affairs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws: for they maintain themſelves by their labour, and cannot have any time to be idle.</hi> Other Common-weals, fill'd with a multitude of Opificers and Mechanicks, he judgeth in far worſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe the life of ſuch men is unactive and ſedentary, and their employment of no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance unto virtue. It appears hence, how vain and frigid that vulgar objection is, (which <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> mentions) againſt the Jews: <hi>In that Nation there are no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventors of new works, no Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers:</hi> This is no diſgrace to the Jews, but the greateſt praiſe; for how can the invention be praiſe worthy, when the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the things invented is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169754:28"/>illiberall? All Opificers are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in works that foul their hands; and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith well, they ſerve a kind of ſervitude, but limited, becauſe we uſe their hands and labour, not as of ſervants in all, but in ſome one matter. So little of what is ingenuous can be found in the Shop, wherein, beſide the reſt, there is alſo this evill, that it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminates and weakens both the body and mind. Wherefore in antient Common-weals well eſtabliſht, (as the moſt judicious Maſter ſaith) Opificers were not Free-men, but ſtrangers, and they were a body as it were diſtinct and ſeparate from the Citizens.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:169754:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The Hebrews hated by the Egyptians, and why. The Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians given to idle Arts: emaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated by</hi> Seſoſtris. <hi>An Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Law of inheriting trades. The Shepheards, a third of the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, feared by the reſt: and why more hated than Husbandmen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw it will be eaſy to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the cauſe why the Jews were hated alwaies by the Egyptians, not only while they ſojourned there, but afterward when they had a proper ſeat and a Common-weal of their own in the neighbouring Land of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> bounded on the South with <hi>Egypt,</hi> as <hi>Cornelius Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> relates. Truly, that hatred ſprang from nothing more, than a diſſimilitude of life and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. For all the Plebeians of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169754:29"/>
                  <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſet upon ſellulary arts, under the ſhade of their Cities took their eaſe within the Wals; Yea ſome, perverting the offices of the virile ſex, handled the ſpinning wheel. And as they were ever prone by their own diſpoſition unto ſoftneſs, ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward were their minds more enervated by the King <hi>Seſoſtris;</hi> Whoſe ſtudie it was to ſoften his people, and as the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans themſelves report, learned the skill of <hi>Mercury.</hi> There was a Law too, that conduced to this end by confining their wit within narrow bounds: for no Opificer might exerciſe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Art, but that which deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to him from his Father. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venal,</hi> when he would ſmite <hi>Criſpinus</hi> (a man gotten up to high place by evill Arts, and <hi>Caeſars</hi> favour) with a Satyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169754:30"/>jerk, calls him <hi>a Plebeian of</hi> Nilus, <hi>and ſlave of</hi> Canopus. For ſo it was the opinion, that the Prieſts were free, and the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pificers, which were the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, ſervants. But there was another ſort far different from thoſe, a certain third part of the people, which liv'd at diſtance in the plains of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and near the marſhes. Theſe were the Shepheards; active and able men, but execrable to all the Egyptians, becauſe they would not ſuffer them to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in their idle courſe of life. Theſe often made great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, and ſometimes created Kings for themſelves. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Romans in after times, when they eaſily held the reſt of <hi>Egypt</hi> in obedience, placed a ſtronger Garriſon in theſe parts. When you have taken the moſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169754:30"/>exact view of all things, you will find, this was the only reaſon that made the Egyptians, even from the firſt, ſo ill-affected un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Shepheards; becauſe thoſe ſedentary men and opificers could not endure their fierce and lively ſpirits. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when he had decreed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate and depreſs the growing multitude of the Iſraelites, ſpeaks to his men on this wiſe: <hi>The Iſraelites are ſtronger than we. Come, let us deal wiſely, that they encreaſe not, leſt when War ariſes they joyn themſelves unto our enemies, and take arms againſt us.</hi> That opinion I think to be right and true; nor can I aſſent to them, that impute the cauſe of this publick hatred to their ſuperſtition: as if the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, Keepers of Flocks and Herds, could not be ſuffered by
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169754:31"/>that Nation, who reverenced, ſome Sheep, ſome Goats, ſome other fourfooted Beaſts, and would not ſlay them, being perſwaded, there was in them ſomething of divinity. But this Reaſon is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry improbable; for what will they anſwer, when either they ſhall learn out of the Penta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuch, that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Flocks of Sheep; or when they ſhall ſee ſo many monuments of Hiſtories to be produc'd, making manifeſt, that a conſiderable part of the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians (as we have above ſaid) lived in Paſtures, and among Cattle? And yet is that ſaying notable in the Scripture; <hi>All Shepheards are hated by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians.</hi> Of Husbandmen it is not ſo ſpoken: nor indeed could their valour (which was none at all) be feared or hated. For
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169754:31"/>the lazy Clowns had all their hopes placed not in the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious manuring of the ground, but in the River <hi>Nilus.</hi> The overflowing ſtream bred and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſt their Corn: nor did it bring only fruitfulneſs to the earth, but earth it ſelf; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mixt with much mud, it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larg'd the Fields, and by an yearly addition ſtretched out the bounds of their Land. So, the Countryman admired both his ſoyl and Crop newly ſprung, which without his labour and care had fallen to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:169754:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>The Jubily not celebrated after the Captivity. That ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was kept in the</hi> 49. <hi>year, which was the</hi> 7. <hi>ſabbaticall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COncerning the Egyptians, what diſpoſition they were of, and how different from their Neighbours of <hi>Judea,</hi> wee have ſpoken ſufficiently; We return, to ſay a little more of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bily. The Agrarian Law made by <hi>Moſes</hi> touching the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of poſſeſſions was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with very great Religion untill the deſolation of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſanctuary by the Aſſyrians. After that, <hi>Paleſtin</hi> lay forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and incult for the ſpace of 70. years, as the Prophets had foretold. But when at length that fatall time was expired,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169754:32"/>the Jews indeed returned to their antient habitations, and the Temple was built a-new, but never was the Agrarian Law revived, nor the Jubily ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities celebrated any more. No more now did every fiftieth year give liberty to ſervants, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore unto the former Lords their loſt and ſold poſſeſſions. Whether juſtly the fiftieth year or the forty ninth was the year of Jubily, 'tis made a queſtion. We joyn with thoſe incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable men of our time that hold the forty ninth: nor can we aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto <hi>Maimonides</hi> in this, though for the moſt, we religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly embrace his judgement. For this Author hath recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced us, for his few and little er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, with many great virtues, and very choice obſervations every where. It is obſerved by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169754:33"/>the ſame <hi>Maimonides,</hi> that as to the intermiſſion of Agricul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, there is the ſame reaſon of the Jubily and every ſeventh year; nor is this a conjecture of the Jews only, or a probable opinion, but certain and undoubted truth, which the Legiſlators own word confirms, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25. But now, if the 50, year exactly were the Jubily, two Sabbaticall years (for the 49. is Sabbaticall) would with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion have been ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated together. A ſingular, ſtrange and unuſuall thing. For, whereas providence had ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that every ſixt year in <hi>Paleſtin,</hi> by its exceeding fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, ſhould prevent the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of the ſeventh, being the year of reſt to the Fields, there muſt now be a more miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous fruitfulneſs, if two years
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169754:33"/>of reſt ſhould come together. In neither was it lawfull to Plow or Sow. Therefore, the divine bounty, which is expreſſed in <hi>Levit. (I will ſend my bleſſing upon you in the ſixt year, and it ſhall bring forth the fruits of three years)</hi> muſt be encreaſed to ſerve for four years, the 49. and 50. being, upon divers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, both Sabbaticall. No ſuch fruitfulneſs was ever granted to any other Land or Nation. We confeſs indeed the Land of <hi>Paleſtin</hi> was the favourite of Heaven, and much indebted to the divine influence above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lands; yea, things went there ſometimes contrary to the Laws of Nature. Nevertheleſs, ſeeing none of the Prophets have given teſtimony to ſo great a miracle, nor any hiſtories have made any record of it, we muſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169754:34"/>not, by too eaſy a credulity, give occaſion to our Reader to charge us with ſtupidity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The three conſecrations of</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtin <hi>and of the Cities; Of City<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>and her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges.</hi> Agrippa<hi>'s offence, and the Jews embaſſage upon it to</hi> Nero. <hi>Of enlarging their terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories: and the right of fortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The ruin of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. The Cities of refuge.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Talmudiſts</hi> affirm, when <hi>Joſuah</hi> marched into <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtin,</hi> he conſecrated all the walled Cities. This they called <hi>the firſt entrance.</hi> But when the holy people was carried
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169754:34"/>away by the Babylonians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Euphrates,</hi> their Country was polluted by the wicked: Wherefore, after the return of the Jews into their ſeats, <hi>Ezra</hi> the high Prieſt, by a ſolemn act, reſtored ſanctimony to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and that was <hi>the ſecond en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance.</hi> At laſt <hi>Caeſar Titus,</hi> having overthrown the Jews, prophaned all again. And here the <hi>Talmudiſts</hi> flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a pleaſing error. For they doe yet expect <hi>Meſſias,</hi> who, as they would have it, ſhall invade the kingdom of <hi>Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> and conſecrate the Cities once more. This, ſay they, will be <hi>the third entrance.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the ſame Authors tell us, wherein conſiſts the Religion and ſanctimony of Cities; and why the Villages and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try were not conſecrated alſo:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169754:35"/>Which it would be tedious to relate. When the Towns of <hi>Paleſtin</hi> were aſſigned to the ſeverall tribes, the <hi>Levites</hi> too received Cities for their habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but the Country, the Fields and poſſeſſions were ſo divided, that they had no ſhare: For they had the Tenths only, and firſt fruits, and all the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices. Of theſe they lived, and with theſe they did abound. But we muſt obſerve with <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monides,</hi> what is here ſaid hath place only in the Land, which by Covenant was given to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, I ſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and which was held by their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and divided amongſt them. But in other regions, which were ſubdued by ſome Kings of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> the Prieſts and Levites had their portion with the reſt of the Hebrews. Concerning City-dwellings
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169754:35"/>there was a Law, that he who had ſold his Houſe might redeem it within a year: the year being paſt, it was the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; nor had the next of Kin any right to redeem it, nor was the Jubily here of any benefit. If the Houſe were redeemed, the whole price was repayed to the buyer, although the ſale and delivery had been made many months before. And the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer poſſeſſor might redeem his Houſe, even on the laſt day of the year. In caſe he was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, who had bought it, or was gone out of the way on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the Redeemer addreſſed himſelf to the Court, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving there in preſence of the Senate laid down the price he had received, departed, brake open the doors, and took poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his Houſe again. Thus
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169754:36"/>the <hi>Talmudiſts.</hi> In the Cities of the Levites it was not ſo but, for their houſes, they had the benefit of the ſame Law which was eſtabliſht by <hi>Moſes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Fields and rurall poſſeſſions of all the Hebrews, as hath been ſaid. Wherefore they might redeem them after the year was paſt; and what was not before redeemed, the Jubily reſtored. Amongſt all the Cities, moſt eminent was <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſanctity, and (as the <hi>Talmud</hi> delivers) it remain'd perpetuall, ever ſince the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication by the moſt glorious King <hi>Salomon:</hi> That <hi>Ezra</hi> conſecrated it again, was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, for it was not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be prophan'd, like other Cities, by the hands of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious. Whence it came to paſs, (as the <hi>Talmud</hi>-tradition
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169754:36"/>is, that it was lawfull to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſe at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and to feaſt upon the ſacrifices, even in the duſt and aſhes of the deſtroyed City. But how great was the Religion of the place, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by thoſe Jews, whom <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> the Emperour permitted once a year to viſit the deformed reliques of the holy City, and there to lament and deplore the miſery of their Nation. This City was not aſſigned by lot unto any one tribe, but was common to them all: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Talmudiſts</hi> free it from that Law, which commands the bloud ſecretly ſhed in the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Tribes, to be expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſlaving of a Heifer. This which follows is not from ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition but from the antient and approved cuſtom of the Nation. <hi>Maimonides</hi> relates,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169754:37"/>if any had an upper room ſo high that it gave them a proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to the Holy of Holies, they might indeed once a week go up to ſee all ſafe, but oftner or for other cauſe, they might not Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily King <hi>Agrippa</hi> much offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his people when from a lofty room in his palace he took a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent view of the Temple &amp; ſaw from on high what was done within it. The Jews, thinking this to be an unſufferable thing, raiſed a high wall to cut off the Kings proſpect, and without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay ſent unto <hi>Rome</hi> ten Legates, with <hi>Iſmael</hi> the High-Prieſt, and <hi>Eleazar</hi> the Treaſurer, to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition <hi>Nero</hi> for a confirmation of that, which Religion had compell'd the people to do. What <hi>Hec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>taeus</hi> of <hi>Abdera</hi> ſaith in <hi>Flavius,</hi> that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was of 50. furlongs compaſs,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169754:37"/>inhabited by one hundred twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand perſons, were not very materiall for us to know, but that there is ſomething of ſingular note concerning the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of their <hi>pomaeria,</hi> which <hi>Maimonides</hi> hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared out of the Talmudicall Books. And this it is. In the enlargement of the City, the great Senate <hi>Sanhedrin,</hi> and the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and one Prophet, conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the oracle called <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim.</hi> After that they had agreed among themſelves about the interpretation of the divine anſwer, the Senators of the <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> recited two Verſes of thankſgiving, and having taken two Loaves of leavened Bread, and departing preſently with inſtruments of Muſick, made a ſtand at the turning of every Sticet, and at all Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169754:38"/>erected in the City, and pronounced theſe words: <hi>I will extoll thee O Lord, becauſe thou haſt lifted me up.</hi> At laſt, when they were come unto the place deſigned for conſecration, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was to be the bound of their <hi>pomaeria,</hi> they all ſtayed; and there, of the two Loaves taken with them, after the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſung, they eat one; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they burnt in the flames. Theſe things received from their Anceſtors, the Talmudicall wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have thus left upon record. Nor are they improbable, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the like and almoſt the ſame are exſtant in the 12. Chapter of <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> commentaries. Yet in after times, the liberty of the Jews being oppreſt by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, this prolation of their <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeria</hi> depended not upon the pleaſure of the great Councill, but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169754:38"/>of the Roman people. Farther, this is alſo deliver'd by <hi>Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> that the Jews, with a great ſum of money purchaſed leave to fortify. Whence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, the Queen of Cities, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> was in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition with all towns under the Roman power, whoſe Walls could not be repair'd without the Authority of the Prince or Governour, nor any thing joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to them, or ſet upon them: as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 9. <hi>ſect. ff. de rerum diviſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ulpian</hi> the Lawyer ſaith. And truly, <hi>Claudius Caeſar,</hi> when he had received intelligence that they were encloſing <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> with a mighty Wall, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed <hi>Agrippa</hi> of that new attempt; and thereupon the King, in obedience to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, left off the work he had undertaken. The Talmudicall writers ſay, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had this
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169754:39"/>privilege, above other Towns of <hi>Judaea,</hi> that no houſe in the City, after one year, could be retained by the buyer. They ſay alſo, it was not lawfull to plant Orchards or gardens there affirming that of the whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which <hi>Hecataeus</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the circuit of the Temple. Dead bodies, which were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried any whither, were not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into that City, out of a reſpect unto the Holineſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Only two Sepulchers were there, of <hi>David,</hi> and of <hi>Olda,</hi> built (they ſay) by the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. Yet were the Levits bound up with a more ſtrict Religion being prohibited to bury the dead in their Cities and in the Field of their Suburbs too. Wherefore, by divine appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they received from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tribes a parcell of ground
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169754:39"/>without their own borders, where they might lay the bones of their dead to reſt. In other Towns, it was not unlawfull to bury, provided ſeven honeſt men gave aſſent thereto; but when once the Corps was carried forth of the gate, it might not be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved again within the walls, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all the people ſhould deſire it. <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as we ſaid above, was the head city, the ſeat of Religion and holy rites; Wherefore, that being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, there fell with it the form of the Jewiſh Common-weal, both Civill and ſacred. Truly what <hi>Flavius</hi> ſaith of a voice heard out of the Temple, before the deſtruction of the City, <hi>Let us go hence;</hi> ſeemeth unto me to ſignifie nothing elſe, but that the Common-weal was to be diſſolved, and the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169754:40"/>Scepter to be taken away, which of old was given to the holy Nation. For within a ſhort time, the orders, and functions, and rites, and almoſt all their Laws ceaſed; and there follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great confuſion, deſolation, and diſtraction. Firſt of all the moſt ſacred College of the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideans, that drew its Originall from the Prophets, was now no more; becauſe their cuſtom was, to goe every day to the Temple, and to beſtow volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary charges upon Sacrifices, and upon the Porches and Walls of the Sanctuary. And whereas <hi>Moſes</hi> impoſed upon ſtrangers that ſhould become Proſelytes, the oblation of ſome certain gift, this upon the diſſolution began to be deferred altogether till another time when the third ſanctuary, which they yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169754:40"/>ſhall be built. Nor doe they any more marry their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Widows, which have no Children. And the ſolennity of the Paſſeover, never ſince that time, hath been rightly celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for the Law commanded it ſhould be kept in that place, wherein. God had choſen the ſeat of his houſe. Of ſo much conſequence was the fall of one City it hath changed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted all things, and brought to ruin the Common-wealth of the greateſt people in the world. Concerning other Towns of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daea,</hi> nothing memorable comes into our mind, but that God appointed ſome of them for Cities of refuge that ſuch as had unwittingly ſlain a man might find ſafety and protection there. There did they endure a gentle baniſhment till the High-Prieſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169754:41"/>dyed, whoſe death ſet them all at liberty; ſo that, if happy any had deceaſed before, yet their bones might then be carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sepulchers of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Theſe towns were ſix; and three more ſhall be added to them, ſay the Talmud-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, when the greateſt of Kings, Meſſias, ſhall come upon the earth; to which they refer that of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes,</hi> not ſpoken ſurely in vain, <hi>When the Lord your God ſhall enlarge your borders.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſix Cities, the ſame pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege was granted to the two and forty towns of Levits; but that the ſame writers deny, thoſe places to have been ſafe for them, that underſtood not the benefit of the Law Other things, which may be ſaid of the Right of theſe Cities, together with what the Jews comment
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169754:41"/>upon ſome other towns, we will therefore let paſs, becauſe we cannot poliſh nor grace them by our handling.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>What</hi> Paleſtin <hi>had above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries. The Hebrew Common-wealth could not bee tranſlated into other places. Of the Babylonian Jews: and their power. Of the Scepter, againſt</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imon. <hi>The J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ws Common-wealth bound to</hi> Paleſtin. <hi>No Temple to be built elſewhere.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Common-wealth of the Hebrews had it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning then, when the holy people was brought into the happy land of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Before which time, though in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabian
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169754:42"/>deſerts moſt wholeſome Laws, both ceremoniall and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall, were given by <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God: yet all their force pertained to that Country, wherein as the ſeverall Tribes ſhould have ſeverall Towns, ſo there ſhould be one City ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly appointed, to be the Chamber of the Empire, and ſent of ſacred rites. In the laſt part of the Pentateuch, the moſt wiſe Legiſlator, repeating what he had given in charge before, hath to our purpoſe added theſe expreſs words again and again: <hi>Theſe are the precepts, the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and judgements, which ye ſhall obſerve in the Land which is given you for an inheritance to poſſeſs.</hi> Truly, <hi>Paleſtin</hi> had this excellency above other Countries, that the holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Common-wealth was
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169754:42"/>affixed unto it alone. Had any one led that people out of their proper ſeat, and eſtabliſhed the ſame Common-wealth by the ſame Laws, neither would the Common-wealth have retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned its ſanctimony, nor the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple their Majeſty. Pertinent here and fit to be conſider'd on our way is that ſaying of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 14. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſn. in Hal. Mel. cap.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monides: As it is not lawfull for the Jews to move their ſeats out of</hi> Paleſtin, <hi>ſo neither may they paſs out of</hi> Babylon <hi>into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries.</hi> Without the explication of this, whoſoever read the writings of the Hebrew Maſters will meet with rubs. The truth is, <hi>Maimonides</hi> ſpeaks not of all the Jews, but of them only who were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed away by the enemy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and dwelt at <hi>Babylon</hi> and thereabout. Some
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169754:43"/>of theſe, after 70. years, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into <hi>Paleſtin:</hi> the reſt, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the beneficence of the Kings, under whom they lived, continued at <hi>Babylon,</hi> and fixed their colonies there. The mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of them was very great, and at laſt grew up into a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Tis incredible, what ſtrength theſe exiles had; for they did almoſt ofter both the Miter and the Diadem that is, the Prieſthood and the Kingdom, to <hi>Hircanus,</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtening out of <hi>Part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> unto <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rod;</hi> and to them were committed the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the Babylonian Empire, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Hebrew Prieſt kept in a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrong Tower at <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> of the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>des. Theſe Jews were joyned in a very cloſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance with thoſe of <hi>Pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> The ſame inſtitutions, the ſame courſe of life, the ſame language
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169754:43"/>was common to both ſorts: all things were the ſame. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as God permitted them to dwell at <hi>Babylon</hi> far from their Country, becauſe they were free there from the contagion of any forein cuſtoms; ſo were they denyed to proceed any farther, and to go to any other habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This is the meaning of <hi>Maimonides</hi> where he interprets that of <hi>Jeremy; they ſhall be carried into</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bylon <hi>and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main there.</hi> There is no more queſtion to be made of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. That is very glorious, which ſome wiſe men of the higher form approved and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i,</hi> have conceived of theſe Babylonians. Their opinion is after the fatall relapſe and decay of the affairs and ſtate of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> theſe Babylonian Jews are the only
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169754:44"/>people upon whom was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd the Imperiall dignity, promiſed in that famous Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle:
<note place="margin">Gen. 49.10.</note> 
                  <hi>The Scepter ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from</hi> Juda, <hi>nor a Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from between his feet, untill Shiloh come.</hi> We, who reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the excellent virtues of <hi>Maimonides,</hi> make no ſcruple to reprehend his errours. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, that moſt conſidering Author, in this opinion, whilſt he too much favours his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-mens conceits, forſook his own judgement. I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that the Babylonian Jews had a Common-wealth among themſelves, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred Juſtice to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt of their own Nation that were without <hi>Paleſtin.</hi> Nor do we forget, that ſome Peers, deſcended from the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> alwaies held the principality there. Yet
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169754:44"/>therefore follows not, that which <hi>Rabbi Ben Maimon</hi> would have. For the Scepter, whereof the Oracle was, is nothing elſe, but the Jewiſh Common-wealth, that is, that Prieſtly Kingdom, whereunto the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions and Ceremonies were, not an acceſſion or prop, but the very ſoul and ſpirit. Beſides, the cuſtody of Ceremonies and ſacred Rites did not belong to every City, but one, wherein was the ſanctuary, the peculiar ſeat and habitation of the Deity. That City firſt was <hi>Shiloh,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in the midſt of <hi>Pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtin.</hi> If any ſchiſmatical Jew built a Temple or Altar in other Lands they offended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rights and inviolable Laws of the Common-wealth. There is extant, among the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of hiſtory, the Epiſtle
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169754:45"/>of <hi>Onias</hi> to <hi>Ptolomy</hi> and <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patra;</hi> wherein he accuſeth his Countrvmen becauſe they had built ſanctuaries in the Pheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Cities and elſewhere, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Law: being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf guilty of no leſs fault ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving built a Temple at <hi>Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,</hi> pretending the Authority of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance his ambitions enterprize. This could not be done without violation of the Cerem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nies. It was amongſt the decrees of the moſt antient Jews, which <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi Moſes Egyptius</hi> delivers thus:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 8. <hi>in Hal. Biath. c. ult.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>If one hath tranſgreſſed the Law, and built an other houſe beſide the ſanctuary at</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>it is not indeed to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a temple of I dols; but yet the Prieſt that hath ſerved there, can never ſacrifice at the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary of God, which is at</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169754:45"/>
                  <hi>Yea the veſſels, which he hath uſed, no man ſhall apply to the Miniſtries of the true ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, but they muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Criminall cauſes judged only in</hi> Paleſtin, <hi>not by the Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Jews and others. When the Common-weal was of all the Hebrews, when of the Jews. What the Scepter was. The plauſible opinion of</hi> Euſebius <hi>confuted. Wherein conſiſts and to whom belongs Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat we have now ſaid of the ſanctuary is of great moment to the confuting of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>monides:</hi> but wee muſt produce other Arguments to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169754:46"/>prove, that the Common-wealth of which old <hi>Jacob</hi> ſpake to <hi>Juda</hi> on his death Bed, was no where ſeated but in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtin.</hi> We will not go far; but cite <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>monides</hi> for a witneſs againſt himſelf. How often doth he tell us, the holy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, without the bounds of the Holy L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd, was looſed from many of the Moſaicall Laws? He hath a notable
<note n="*" place="margin">In Hala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha ſanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drin.</note> d ſſertation, wherein he circumſcribes with certain limits the power of the Judges, both of <hi>Paleſtin,</hi> and <hi>Babylon.</hi> Certainly, the greateſt part of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes</hi> Law is conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant about criminall cauſes. The judgement hereof, ſaith <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> could be no where exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Babylonian Jews, no not in <hi>Paleſtin.</hi> And the Jews of <hi>Paleſtin,</hi> as by the Law they gave judgement to their
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169754:46"/>own people in all cauſes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their own Country; ſo, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, they gave no ſentence upon their Country-men, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by the permiſſion of the Babylonian Peers, or other heads of the exiled Jews. Whence we gather, that the Jews of <hi>Paleſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> judged of crimes, in their own Country alwaies, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Law; ſometimes out of their Country, but by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and leave of others: the Babylonians no where judged of them; not in their own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, not in <hi>Paleſtin;</hi> not by force of Law, nor by permiſſion. And are theſe the men, think you, to whom was given the Jewiſh Scepter, after the affairs of <hi>Paleſtin</hi> were broken and decayed? Surely either the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent writer knew not what was the dignity of the Scepter,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169754:47"/>or he thought too well of ſome States of ſtraw, that do there boaſt themſelves to be of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> houſe. But wee wonder not at this light miſtake of <hi>Maimonides,</hi> when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by what ſtrange interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions others have laboured for the ſenſe of <hi>Jacobs</hi> divine ſpeech. I remember, I had conference, concerning this, with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Apollonius Scottus</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor of the ſupreme Senate, at what time in his houſe at the <hi>Hague,</hi> I ſweetly ſpent the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and with great ardor ran over the Luculent commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of <hi>Rabbi Ben Maimon:</hi> wherewith I was ſo taken, that I croſſed almoſt all my former notes concerning the Jewiſh State. There did this Senator, ſuch is his learning and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding vigor of his wit, ſignifie
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169754:47"/>more than once, that in his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment no other Text in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Book is more examined by learned men, and leſs under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. Verily I was glad to find of my opinion a man, whoſe authority and repute might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me to oppoſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations of any other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. Wherefore by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citement. I think I ſhall not do amiſs if in ſo great a multitude of conjectures. I ſhall alſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh what my judgment is, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a prophecy ſo illuſtrious. The Argument indeed is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, wherein the wit of every man may exerciſe it ſelf, and ſhew its ſtrength. Although in this our Treatiſe we handle the affairs of Hebrews and Jews in common and without diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, for the moſt part, yet to ſecure the Reader from miſtake,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169754:48"/>we will once for all demonſtrate, that the ſacred Common-wealth conſtituted by <hi>Moſes</hi> according to Gods appointment, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the ſame, and founded on the ſame Laws, but not alwaies of the ſame perſons. A long time it was of the Hebrews, afterward by change of times it was only of the Jews. And ſo, the oracle of <hi>Jacob,</hi> which is of <hi>Juda's</hi> Scepter, pertaineth only to thoſe later times. The ignorance whereof is the cauſe why this admirable prophecy hath been hitherto miſunderſtood. I will not mention here the miſerable hallucinations of <hi>Origen, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, Epiphanius</hi> and others, who thought the Jews were promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by thoſe words of <hi>Jacob,</hi> a perpetuall ſucceſſion of Kings of the ſame tribe and the ſame linage, even to the times of Meſſiah. An opinion which led
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169754:48"/>the followers of it into inſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable difficulties; for they know not what to ſay, nor whither to turn themſelves, when they ſaw, from the death of <hi>Sedechiah</hi> to the times of <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> the Kingdom of the Jews was none; and after that untill <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> tyranny, it was in the hands only of the <hi>Haſmonaei</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Levi.</hi> Theſe things of late are diſcuſſed well, and with good ſucceſs, in the exercitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt <hi>Baronius,</hi> by the moſt learned man of our age <hi>I ſaack Caſaubon,</hi> who is pleaſed with the famous opinion of <hi>Euſebius</hi> extant in the eighth Book of his Evangelicall demonſtrations. We pretermit all things rightly ſaid both by <hi>Euſebius</hi> and by <hi>Caſaubon,</hi> that we may not do what is done to our hand. And we confeſs, among all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169754:49"/>hitherto divulged, that of <hi>Euſebius</hi> is far the beſt. But becauſe neither <hi>Euſebius,</hi> nor that great Scholar that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows him, ſeem to me to have underſtood, what that Scepter is, of which the old Prophet ſpeaks to his Son a little before his death, nor when it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Jews, this is needfull now to be cleared, but not without a preface. For it is no pleaſure to us to diſſent, neither from <hi>Euſebius,</hi> whom we have ever eſteemed among the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt writers; nor from him, whom we have above named, the prime man of our age, the follower of <hi>Euſebius;</hi> to whom we owe ſo much reverence, that no man is ſo great with us, as He. For He it is, by whoſe conduct theſe our times have made ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable proficiency toward the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169754:49"/>perfection of all learning. But we are conſtrained by our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous love of truth, to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide affection, and impartially inquire what is right. The firſt error of <hi>Eùſebius</hi> is, that the Scepter was given to <hi>Juda</hi> even from the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this Tribe excelled alwaies among the reſt, with ſingular dignity, and held a more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable place both in the Camps and in the order of them that offered gifts in the Temple. Which Argument moves me no more, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if one ſhould ſay, the Majeſty of the Scepter, at <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or <hi>Athens,</hi> was not in the Roma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> Athenian people, but in one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which was more noble or flou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing For tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is manifeſt by the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant affirmation of antient Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, that in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Athens</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:169754:50"/>both; were many and divers tribes, ſome above the reſt in dignity, place and order. What is it then? Verily I ſuppoſe the Scepter to be nothing elſe, but the Majeſty of Empire, Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty I mean pertaining to the Common-wealth it ſelf; Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whoſe is the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, theirs alſo is the Scepter. Now, the Hebrew Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, from the age of <hi>Moſes</hi> until the reign of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> was not of the Jews, but of the twelve tribes. Whence it follows, that the Scepter, all that ſpace of time, was of all the Iſraelites. But of this Scepter, which a long time was common to all the tribes, the divine Patriarch ſpoke not in that celebrious oracle. He had reſpect unto the later times and the ages to come, when the tribe of <hi>Juda,</hi> the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169754:50"/>people being divided into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary parts, began to have a Common-wealth of their own, a ſunder from the Iſraelites: a Common-wealth approved and favoured of God, and called Judaicall from the name of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> alone, untill he ſhould come, who was deſigned for the King not of the Jews only, but of all Nations. And this Majeſty of the Scepter, from the time it once began to be the Jews, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued theirs, although the State of the Common-wealth was ſometimes altered, and the power was in the hand, one while of the beſt men and the Prieſts, other while of the Kings and Princes. It is want of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in them that reſtrain the honour of this Title to Kings alone. For what people ſoever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys a Common-wealth of their
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169754:51"/>own, and Laws of their own, that people may juſtly glory in their Empire, and in their Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It is recorded, that in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> even at the time when the people were govern'd not by Princes but by the beſt, in the midſt of the Great Councill, which they call <hi>Sanhedrin,</hi> there hang'd a Scepter. Which was, no queſtion, a certain token of that Majeſty, which
<note n="*" place="margin">In part. orat.</note> 
                  <hi>Tully</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth <hi>to be a certain greatneſs of a people, in retaining that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and right, which appears in Empire and all kind of Honour.</hi> Not Kings, not Princes, but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls and Senators managed the Roman Common-wealth, when that Law of confederation was given to the Etolians (as <hi>Livy</hi> relates) <hi>that they ſhould well and truly conſerve the Majeſty of the Roman people.</hi> And that the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169754:51"/>ſame was impoſed upon all free people that were confederates (but upon unequall terms) and friends to the Romans, the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In l.</hi> 7. <hi>ff. de captiv. &amp; poſtlim. reverſis.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Proculus</hi> is a witneſs. Neither is it materiall to us, of what family or tribe they were, who governed the Judaicall State. For, although the <hi>Haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaei</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years poſſeſſed the Kingdom, nevertheleſs was the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of the Jewiſh people. <hi>Nero Caeſars</hi> moſt wiſe
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi>
                  </note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter told him, <hi>The Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth is not the Princes, but the Prince the Common-weal's.</hi> And <hi>Ulpian</hi> the Lawyer was juſt of the ſame opinion: <hi>The crime of Majeſty,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1. <hi>ff. ad lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem Jul. Majeſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>or Treaſon</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is that which is committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Roman people, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſecurity thereof. Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> lived in thoſe times, when
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169754:52"/>neither the commands nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages were in the people, but the <hi>Caeſars</hi> held the Empire and power of all: yet he, that is wont moſt accurately to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine every thing, aſcribeth Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to the people.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>The twelve Tribes of the Hebrews was never called by the name of Jews. The ten tribes car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried captive by</hi> Salmanaſſar <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver returned into</hi> Paleſtin. <hi>Two tribes ſerved the Romans, and no more, in the time of</hi> Joſephus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EUſebius</hi> is not ſufficiently confuted, untill wee have made it plain how imprudently he drew himſelf into the ſnare.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 8. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt. evan. dem.</hi> 1.</note> In the forecited Book are extant
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169754:52"/>theſe words: <hi>Ever ſince the time of</hi> Moſes, <hi>the Governours of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>if you look upon them in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, were choſen out of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall tribes, but in generall the tribe of Juda was over the whole Nation.</hi> Hitherto he agrees with himſelf and falls into no contradiction; but he addes, <hi>For example, as in the Roman Empire, the Governours of ſeveral Nations, and Camp-maſters, and the Kings, greater than all the reſt were not all born at</hi> Rome, <hi>nor deſcended from</hi> Romulus <hi>and</hi> Remus, <hi>but ſprung of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations, ſome of one, ſome of another; and yet, as well all the Kings, as the ſucceeding Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours and Leaders, were called Romans, and the power and authority ſaid to be of the Romans, not of any other name: ſo muſt we think of the Hebrew
<pb facs="tcp:169754:53"/>State, that one tribe of</hi> Juda <hi>gave an illuſtrious name to all the reſt, though the Rulers and Kings were created out of the ſeverall tribes, all honoured with the common appellation of Jews.</hi> See whither incogitancy will bring a man! <hi>Euſebius</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes contrary to what himſelf would have. For, affirming the Scepter was the Jews from <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> time; he proves it by this reaſon, becauſe the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the Empire, and the whole people of twelve tribes, had their appellation from the one name of <hi>Juda.</hi> With this argument twice or thrice in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places he triumpheth; and you ſhall hardly find any other proof of his opinion in the whole diſcourſe. But, by his leave, all this is nothing. For, neither did the Common-wealth,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169754:53"/>nor the Empire begin to be called after <hi>Juda</hi>'s name, till after the greater part of the Iſraelites, had made a defection, drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who ſhortly at <hi>Samaria</hi> ſtrenthened his Kingdom by introducing a change of ceremonies and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. I will make it good to <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and to all that have any acquaintance with ſacred ſtory, that this is ſo. <hi>Euſebius</hi> often and with confidence af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, all the twelve tribes were called by the name of Jews, and hath obtruded this groundleſs opinion upon unwary men, nor have there been wanting ſome writers of greateſt eminence to defend it. We cannot yield un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: whether you reſpect the times antecedent to the ſeiſure of the Kingdom, or ſubſequent. And, we may conjecture, that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169754:54"/>
                  <hi>Euſebius,</hi> although he doth not plainly expreſs his mind, thought it came to paſs at the riſe of the Empire when the Common-wealth was firſt ſetled in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and it was deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by what name to call it. But this hath no colour of truth, wherefore that excellent man, the Defender of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> makes him think otherwiſe of the time, and what he believes he thought, himſelf approves and follows. For, ſaith he, it was obſerved by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that the twelve tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> received appellation from the name of <hi>Juda;</hi> and the appellation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be uſed, when the Kingly power, which the tribe of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> had loſt in <hi>Sedechiah,</hi> was by the High Prieſts tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon themſelves. And this, ſaith he, is a thing moſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169754:54"/>worthy of admiration, and fell out by ſpeciall providence. For, ſeeing in <hi>Polybius</hi> his opinion 'twas not without ſome great cauſe that the Acheians, a little people of <hi>Greece,</hi> once gave name to all the Grecians; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here alſo we muſt conceive ſome more ſublime and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reaſon, when after the return from captivity all the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> of all the tribes were called Jews. This errour we neither can, nor ought to excuſe. The truth is this: When the Kingdom of the Iſraelites was rent and divided, two tribes, <hi>Levi</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelves with the Jews; which tribes being but few in number, and of mean eſtate, were accounted but for an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; the Common-wealth was not named from them, but
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169754:55"/>they even loſt their own name, and at length the name of Jews was common to them all. There is no doubt to be made of thus much. But what, or how this can concern the other ten tribes, let them conſider that are pleaſed with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit. Certainly, after that thoſe ten tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were once carried away by <hi>Salmanaſſar</hi> the Aſſyrian, and diſperſed through <hi>Colchos, Parthia, India,</hi> and <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> they never came back again into their native ſoil, nor were again conjoyned with the Jews: but even to this day, (if there be any reliques of them) under the command of barbarous Nations, they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the grievous puniſhment of their Apoſtacy. Wherefore, to be in the Common-wealth of the Jews, or to have the honour
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169754:55"/>a name from the Jews, was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſble for them who had no familiarity, nothing to do with the Jews, but were ſeated in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother World far off, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held a different Heaven, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Stars. It will be worth our pains, and much to the preſent diſpatch, to examine a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable place, that is in <hi>Flavius Joſephus,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>Antiquit.</hi>
                  </note> an Author of exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit and unuſuall diligence, <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> had ſpoken firſt concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, who from every quarter out of the neighbouring places came to <hi>Babylon,</hi> that they might return with <hi>Ezra</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> They all were Jews, and their Aſſociates of <hi>Levi</hi> and <hi>Benjamin.</hi> And then, concerning the Hebrews of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tribes, he addes: <hi>But all the people of</hi> Iſrael <hi>remained in their</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Where they were carried by <hi>Salmanaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> beyond <hi>Euphrates.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſeats; wherefore both in</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:169754:56"/>Aſia <hi>and in</hi> Europe, <hi>two tribes only fell under the dominion of the Romans; the other ten do ſtill continue on the other ſide of</hi> Euphrates, <hi>being infinite in number and unknown.</hi> Verily, they were under a harder fate, whom <hi>Salmanaſſar</hi> led into captivity, than whom afterward <hi>Nebuchodonozor</hi> carried away. For the Iſraelites were for ever reſtrained and kept back by the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> which they had once paſſed over. But the Jews paſſed the ſame, and repaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and came again at laſt into <hi>Paleſtin:</hi> and when <hi>Paleſtin</hi> it ſelf became either too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for them, or leſs gratefull, they enlarged and ſpred their habitations through <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia.</hi> This is the reaſon why <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſaid, only two tribes of the Hebrews were brought
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169754:56"/>into ſubjection by the Romans. For at that time the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> although they had almoſt ſubdued the World, and the Sun did both riſe and ſet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſs of their Empire, being Lords of the Eaſt and Weſt, they had not yet extended their bounds beyond <hi>Euphrates.</hi> Therefore, that the ten tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſhut up in eternall priſon by that River, were not then under the Roman power, was truly ſaid by the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate Writer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:169754:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Their Conjecture that ſay the Scepter of</hi> Juda <hi>was firſt given to</hi> David. <hi>The prophecy concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Scepter not fulfilled till after times. When the Scepter was taken away.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have ingenuouſly and freely ſpoken my opinion, when the Scepter, whereof <hi>Jacobs</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy is extant, was given to the Jews: alſo, what were the members of that Common-wealth, which had its riſe and beginning from the Seceſſion of the common people. Theſe things <hi>Euſebius</hi> did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: yet he alone, among ſo many Interpreters, hath rightly and almoſt divinely judged of that oracle. The comments of other men I will not relate. But,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169754:57"/>what <hi>Euſebius</hi> affirms to have been done from the beginning of the Hebrew Common-wealth, very many conjecture, came to paſs at that time, when the royall power was devolved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>David,</hi> deſcended of the tribe of <hi>Juda,</hi> as the ſacred Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory doth witneſs. Theſe men have already received ſuch a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and happy confutation from <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that no place is left here for the induſtry of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For he ſhews, that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> poſterity poſſeſſed the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom only for a ſmall time, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Babylonian captivity: and the ſundry Scriptures that ſpeak of his eternall throne, he hath well and wiſely interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in relation to the Meſſias. To adde more of this after <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius,</hi> were to labour in vain; for by his pains herein, he hath
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169754:58"/>eaſed every one. It remains only, that wee anſwer their doubt, who wonder why the event came ſo far behind the prediction concerning the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Common-wealth. For we have ſaid, it began under <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> and not before. But we give them to underſtand, this was very agreeable to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the prophetick Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch. For the old Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death, breathing forth his laſt words to his children, ſaith, he would tell them, <hi>what ſhould come to paſs in the later dayes.</hi> Beſides, in prophecies, the times are not curiouſly to be inſiſted on: for moſt of them are to be interpreted with very great latitude. Obſerve, in this very prophecy, when it is ſaid, <hi>The Scepter ſhall not be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, untill Shiloh come;</hi> you
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169754:58"/>would think 'twere meant, that preſently upon the appearance of Meſſias, the Scepter ſhould be ſnatcht out of the hands of that Nation. Which came not ſo to paſs. For the Jews loſt not that honour, till the City being deſtroyed, and the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple burnt, they ceaſed to have any Common-wealth, and to govern themſelves by their own Laws. Nevertheleſs, the oracle was infallibly true. For although the Saviour of the World had left the earth long before, yet, for certain, theſe things hapned in the ſame age: which was preſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by the Meſſias himſelf, wher he ſpeaks of the deſtruction of the City and Temple, in theſe words: <hi>Verily,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>this Generation ſhall not paſs, till all theſe things be fulfilled.</hi> This is enough for the wiſe. The reſt, that love to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169754:59"/>raiſe doubts and ſcruples every where, we regard not. For my part, ſeeing men of great name fluctuating among uncertain er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, I applyed my ſelf to find out ſome firm ground to reſt on, which henceforth I might without danger conſtantly maintain. For otherwiſe this matter would have often hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred our proceeding in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:169754:59"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of Dictators and Judges. Of the Senate Sanhedrin. Of the initiation of Senators. The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands: and the ſolemn words. Who were choſen into that Council, and what was their juriſdiction. Of the peoples aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE have ſhewed, that the Common-wealth, of which we diſcourſe, was of all the Hebrews for a long time, and then only of the Jews. The ſtating whereof concern'd us much. Now, having paſt the trouble of that diſpute, let us declare who they were that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led over the Holy Nation, and what is to be thought of their judicature, and of their Senate. The Divine goodneſs granted
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169754:60"/>not leave to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to behold in <hi>Paleſtin</hi> the beginnings of that Common-wealth, whoſe Laws he had publiſhed in the wilderneſs. That Grace was vouchſafed to his Succeſſor <hi>Joſuah,</hi> the Captain General and Soveraign of the people; for both at home, and abroad in the War, his word was a Law. His Succeſſors with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall power were they, who, for going in and out before the people, and commanding them, might well be called Praetors and Dictators, but in the ſacred Annals are, for the like reaſon, named Judges. <hi>Flavius</hi> hath ſtil'd them Monarchs, a name, that the Greek writers gave al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to <hi>Sylla, Cinna, Marius,</hi> and other Roman Dictators. Theſe Judges, in great commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, were created by neceſſity:
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169754:60"/>and experience witneſſed, that in War they had alwaies good ſucceſs, when the Kings very often had their raſhneſs requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ill fortune. Sometime alſo the ſame Judges were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in civill affairs, and heard cauſes, but thoſe of the greater moment. For they ſeldom ſate in the judgment ſeat. Only the commands, and the Empire, and the Soveraingty pertained unto them. The laſt of their number was <hi>Samuel,</hi> He, whom the Kings followed. Who not content with power and rule, lifted up themſelves above the multitude, in their robes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments and ſplendor of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. Moreover, beſides the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Rulers and Judges of the people, and thoſe that were after called Kings, there were others not a few, who conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169754:61"/>of the Common-wealth, gave judgment, and arbitrated buſineſs. For there were certain Synedryes or Councils; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, who were the Senators, and what where the matters of their cognizance, we muſt now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. In the firſt place preſents it ſelf the great Councill of the Sanhedrin, into which were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crib'd ſeventy Adſeſſors. That Council, conſtituted by <hi>Moſes,</hi> continued under the Judges, and Kings, and high Prieſts, untill the laſt deſolation of <hi>Judaea;</hi> and was holden in that City which was the ſeat of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, and the head of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. But becauſe the firſt times, and the next to them, are moſt part obſcure, and the Holy Book hath delivered to us nothing of principall conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration concerning the City <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loh;</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:169754:61"/>We will deliver what the Jews have obſerved of that Council in the Princeſs of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> after the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was built there: and then wee ſhall ſpeak of the other Councils, which were either at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or at particular Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The Seat of the great Council was in the very San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, where the ſeventy Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors judged both of divine and humane things: Men, not cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from among the Plebeians, but all moſt noble, commended by their honourable Parentage, and the antient ornaments of their family. The place was aſſigned to them by <hi>Moſes,</hi> who commanded they ſhould meet in the place which God ſhould chooſe to have his name ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red there. From theſe Judges was no appeal. Whatſoever the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169754:62"/>other Magiſtrates and Judges in the towns of <hi>Paleſtin</hi> and in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> it ſelf were not able to decide, belonged unto their juriſdiction. Two of them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled the reſt in honour and authority: one was the head of the Sanedrin, by the Talmudiſts entitled <hi>Prince in every place;</hi> the other next in degree, but inferiour to him, whom they called <hi>the Father of judgment.</hi> The reſt were equall among themſelves. This Senatorious dignity, becauſe it was moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, was granted to none without a legitimate act, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, impoſition of hands. So, <hi>Moſes</hi> layd his hand upon <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuah</hi> and the ſeventy Elders: which ſolemnity being perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, preſently a divine ſpirit from above fell down upon them, and fill'd their breaſts.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169754:62"/>And theſe, being thus initiated themſelves, admitted others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame way. Yet could not that rite be uſed without the Holy Land, becauſe all the vertue thereof was confined by the bounds of <hi>Paleſtin.</hi> It is very obſerveable, which <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monides</hi> hath delivered in the fourth Chapter of his <hi>Halacha Sanhedrin.</hi> For whereas of old this act was celebrated at their pleaſure, by all thoſe upon whom hands had been once impoſed, that right (ſaith he) was ſtreightned by the wiſe men, and a conſtitution made, that no man ſhould after that time uſe it, but by grant from <hi>Rabbi Hillel,</hi> that divine old man. He was Prince of the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill, and had another vice Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, <hi>Sameas,</hi> a man trucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ambitious; whoſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169754:63"/>when a little after they had riſen up againſt the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Hillel,</hi> ſtirred the minds of men with ſo much paſſion, that willingly the whole peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was drawn into their party. At length this impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands, which had been uſed long, ceaſed. And there was only pronounced a certain form of words (according to <hi>Ben Maimon</hi>) of this ſenſe: <hi>Behold, the hand is impoſed on thee, and power given thee to judge, in criminall cauſes alſo.</hi> Beſides, the Talmudiſts have told us of another form; whoſe words, becauſe the illuſtrious <hi>Joſeph Scaliger</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In elen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ho Trihae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</note> hath miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, we ſhall here reſtore unto their proper ſenſe. The Talmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſts, after they had ſpoken of <hi>Juda</hi> the ſon of <hi>Baba,</hi> a ſtout defender of the antient cuſtoms
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169754:63"/>of his Nation, and who, when the juriſdiction in criminals and impoſition of hands were almoſt loſt, ſupported the ſinking cauſe, adde thus: <hi>That ſolemn act is not only done by the hand impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as</hi> Moſes <hi>did to</hi> Joſuah; <hi>but it is alſo done by a form of words only, after this manner, I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my hand upon thee, and be the hand on thee impoſed.</hi> But the excellent <hi>Scaliger</hi> collected from the place, that <hi>Juda</hi> had found out a form different from the moſt antient, which is there conceived (when 'tis not ſo, nor do the Talmudiſts ſay ſo) being deceived by a word which bee renders, <hi>beſides,</hi> which in Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biniſm ſignifies <hi>only.</hi> But this is a Grammaticall note, and ought to be left to others. We are here to conſider graver mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Into the Great Councill,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169754:64"/>not only Citizens of prime No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, as we have ſaid, but Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits alſo and Prieſts were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. And the High Prieſt (ſaith <hi>Maimonides</hi>) was elected too, if he were a conſidering man, and fit for Counſell. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it was lawfull to lay him aſide. For he came not to the Senate by any right of his own, but he was admitted by ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. All the Adſeſſors were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be entire and perfect in body. Whoſoever had any main or deformity was exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Nor were ſtrangers and foreiners received into this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, except the Mother at leaſt were a Jew. The Senators of the <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> had this charge, to make their progreſs through all <hi>Judea,</hi> to take a view of the Aſſemblies of the people, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them Magiſtrates in every
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169754:64"/>town. And all the vertue and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Cabbala</hi> (a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious doctrine delivered from hand to hand even from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth) was with them. Their part alſo it was, to make Statutes in ſacred matters, and to deviſe certain wayes to expound the Law. Whereof <hi>Maimonides</hi> hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with great care. Moreover, the cauſes of Prophets, who had highly offended, were no where tryed but in this great Councill. Which our Saviour had reſpect unto, when he ſaid in <hi>Luke, It is not poſſible, that a Prophet ſhould periſh out of</hi> Jeruſalem. Laſtly, which is a point of the greateſt power, they did alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a King, and deliberat of waging War, and giving battail to the enemy, and enlarging the Empire. But becauſe, in theſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169754:65"/>things the common ſafety, and publick ſtate was ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, conſultation was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in had (for the moſt part) with the people. For meetings were called, wherein alone they had ſome ſhare in the Government. And truly, otherwiſe they ought not. Honours and Magiſtracies are committed to ſingle and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect men. <hi>Plebeians</hi> have not ſtrength and skill to bear them. In their meetings (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath diſcreetly noted) and in conjuncture, the multitude hath ſome underſtanding, and can advance the publick good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the wiſer men are preſent and lead the way; but ſingle and apart they have little judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Concerning a King then, and concerning War, as I have ſaid, Decrees were made ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the people being Author:
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169754:65"/>all other things the Senators of <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> diſpatched by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The weightieſt affairs were not too heavy for them, becauſe they were choſen for their worth, and great abilities; by the divine <hi>Moſes</hi> rightly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Elders, not only for their age, but for their wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dom and experience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:169754:66"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of two other Councils at</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem <hi>beſides the</hi> Sanhedrin. <hi>The Senate of</hi> 23. <hi>in every town. The College of</hi> 3. <hi>The meaſure of Cities. The</hi> 5. <hi>men for expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſlaughter. The</hi> 7. <hi>men and</hi> 3. <hi>men for ordering the Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar. The times diſpoſed by</hi> Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi Hillel. <hi>The authority of</hi> San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrin <hi>leſſened.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OF the great Senate we have ſaid, what came to mind: the other Councils will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain us long. The moſt learned
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n Hala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrin. c.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Maimonides</hi> relates, that in the City of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> it ſelf were two Councils more. They are deſcribed in the
<note n="*" place="margin">In Miſna &amp; in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara.</note> 
                  <hi>Talmud.</hi> In either of them ſate three and twenty Judges. And as the Great Council was held in that
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169754:66"/>part of the Temple, which is called <hi>Gazith,</hi> ſo one of theſe at the Court-gate, the other was kept at the Gate opening to the Mount of the Temple. The Dignity of them alſo was not the ſame: for the Judges at the Mount-Gate, took it for a preferment to be aſcrib'd into the Senate at the Court-Gate. And again, it was a new degree of honour to aſcend hence into the <hi>Sanedrin.</hi> The diſtinction is exactly made by <hi>Rabbi Ben Maimon.</hi> Farther, beſide theſe Councils at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> there was conſtituted in every town of <hi>Paleſtin,</hi> a Senate for juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and the care of publick affairs. It conſiſted of 23. men, who ſate in judgement upon the life and fortunes of the people, and decided all cauſes, except a few reſerved, as is aforeſaid,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169754:67"/>to the great Councill. <hi>Ben Maimou</hi> alſo deſcribes a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain College of three men, and ſaith it was in ſuch a City, which had not a hundred and twenty inhabitants. But I am of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotles</hi> mind, that this is not a City. For, as it is not a Ship, which is of one handfull, or of two furlongs: ſo is it not a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which wanteth a juſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; if it be too little, it cannot (as a City ſhould) ſubſiſt by it ſelf; and too much greatneſs turns it from a City to a Nation. But we muſt not call a <hi>Rabbi</hi> to ſo ſtrict account. It was the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of thoſe three, to judge of treſpaſſes of moneys, and goods moveable. The Capitall offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were brought (as I have ſhewed) before another Bench.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hedrin, c.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Ben Maimon</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Halu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrin. c.</hi> 5.</note> addes, ſomethings were of ſuch a kind that they
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169754:67"/>belonged neither to the ſeventy Elders, nor to the College of twenty three, nor to the three men: but were to be referred to a peculiar Senate. In which number he reckons man-ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter committed by an uncertain hand in the borders of any town. Five men (ſaith he) muſt expiate this by the Sacrifice of a Heifer. The ſame Author hath more of this nature, which I willingly praetermit. For we doe not repeat Dictates. That may ſeem ſtrange, that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of times was commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to certain Judges; for,
<note n="*" place="margin">In eadem Halacha, eod. cap.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Leap-year, ſeven, concerning the month, three men determined. But <hi>Hillel</hi> the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian afterward acquitted all his Countrymen of this care: the prime man of his age, of whom we have this honourable
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169754:68"/>teſtimony from <hi>Rabbi Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In libro juchaſin.</note> 
                  <hi>Zacuth:</hi> Rabbi Hillel, <hi>preſident of the great Councill compoſed the Intercalation for all</hi> Iſrael <hi>till the times of Meſſiah; and that was done by him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lawfull act of impoſition of hands was abrogated.</hi> Had not this ſame <hi>Hillel</hi> maturely prevented ſo great an evill, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the times would have been much confuſed; for, not long after ceaſed the ſolennity of impoſing hands, without which thoſe ſeven men and three men were not appointed over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers and correctors of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar, as <hi>Maimonides</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth. But no more of this, leſt the Reader think we prepare an accurate and perfect work, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we only thruſt out our ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain and tumultuary Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And we deſire it may be
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169754:68"/>noted, whatſoever we have ſaid of Councils hath relation to the time before <hi>Judaea</hi> had received the Roman conqueror. For he changed and repealed many things, not for his luſt or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nor out of any cruell deſign, but that he might ſecure his Dominion. <hi>Gabinius</hi> chiefly, the Proconſul of <hi>Syria,</hi> ſeeing the principall pillar of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth was the <hi>Sanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drin,</hi> thought it good policy to take away the authority there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in many towns. Wherefore at <hi>Gadar, Amath, Hiericho,</hi> and <hi>Sephor</hi> he ſetled four Syne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dries, and a fift at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (now but a part of what ſhe was) all of equall power. And the Councils placed by <hi>Gabinius</hi> in the other Cities, as they were not inferiour to that in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> for power, ſo were they
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169754:69"/>far beyond it in continuance. Theſe are meant, if I miſtake not, by
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In l.</hi> 17. <hi>c. de Jud. &amp; Cal.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a Canon, <hi>from the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, who rule the Synedries of either</hi> Paleſtin. But we make no excurſion into theſe times. The antient Common-wealth and primitive Inſtitutions are under our conſideration. To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the reſt, and ſet down things that were often changed, were unhappily to place our ſtudy, where no certain truth can be delivered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:169754:69"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>The creation of a King. A bad one firſt choſen, why. What qualities the Prophet had reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect unto. The Book of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom laid up. The power of the Hebrew Kings. Their honour above Prieſts and Prophets. Kings and Prieſts at firſt the ſame. The annointing of Kings made them ſacred. The Holy Ointment hid by</hi> Joſia, <hi>and loſt with other things.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RAbbi Ben Maimon</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In part. poſt. Miſnae.</note> ſaith, the Iſraelites received three commands from God, to bee fulfilled in <hi>Paleſtin;</hi> the firſt whereof was, to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a King; another to blot out the memory of the Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites; the third concerning the building of a Temple. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169754:70"/>whereof (ſaith he) was at ſeverall times and long diſtant, but in the ſame order wherein they were commanded. For a King was created before the War with <hi>Amalek,</hi> and the building of the Temple was not begun, untill that moſt odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Nation was brought to an end, and quite deſtroyed. The teſtimonies illuſtrious, which are related by the ſame Author, need not be tranſcribed hither. In the 17 of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> the moſt high God, ſaying the Iſraelites would deſire a King, addes the trueſt reaſon of it, becauſe all the neighbouring Nations lived under the royall Government. For ſuch is the nature and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of men, inhabiting that part of the world: few prefer liberty before ſubjection unto juſt Lords. And <hi>Claudius Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilis</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:169754:70"/>in <hi>Tacitus</hi> truly ſaith to his Batavians, <hi>that</hi> Syria <hi>and</hi> Aſia <hi>ſerve, and the Eaſt is accuſtomed to the yoke of Kings.</hi> This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, many have admired, why God took it ill, that the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign power was transferred from <hi>Samuel</hi> to a King, ſince he had approved it before, and ſaid it ſhould be according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the holy people. <hi>Maimonides</hi> anſwers learnedly, that the divine Indignation aroſe from hence, <hi>Becauſe they deſir'd a King by unfaithfull complaints and ſeditious murmurings, not that they might comply with Gods deſign in the Law, but out of a diſtaſt of the moſt holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> Samuel: <hi>to whom it was ſpoken by the voice of God. They have not rejected thee, but me.</hi> Verily I am of this opinion, and I doubt not to aſſert it, that the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169754:71"/>Kingdom was given to <hi>Saul,</hi> not out of Gods love and care of the Common-wealth, but becauſe he perceived his arrogance and cruelty, hee meant to glorify <hi>Samuel</hi> by this unequall compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, and by ſuch a ſucceſſor make his vertue the more deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The qualities ſeem but light and ſuperficiall, but they are of great moment, which (as the Holy Book in ſeverall places hath it) were conſidered by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> in the Kings election: a gracefull look, talneſs of body, and ſuch like, which affect and draw the eyes and minds of all. Theſe are the things, which the great Prophet, in the midſt of the Aſſembly, commended, when he ſpake theſe words:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold, whom God hath choſen: that there is none equall to him in all the people.</hi> Wherefore, it is not
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169754:71"/>the property of Barbarians on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but of the moſt civill men, to think them capable of great atchievements, whom nature hath graced with a goodly form and ſtately countenance. No leſs a man than <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced thus: If any perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are by nature framed ſo much more excellent than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as the images of Gods excell the images of men, it ſeemeth meet, that the reſt ſhould be ſervants unto ſuch. If this be true in the body, much more in the ſoul: but the ſouls form and beauty cannot be ſo eaſily diſcerned. To leave this: In the Holy Bible is mentioned a certain volume,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.25.</note> wherein <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> wrote the ſacred rights of the Kingdom, and laid it up in the Tabernacle. A text not well underſtood by <hi>Joſephus;</hi> who
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169754:72"/>imagined all the evils, which God foretold the people they ſhould fear from an unjuſt King were comprehended in that volume. We on the contrary believe, there were in that Book the Laws, which commanded the King to follow juſtice and equity, and to govern the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth wiſely for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples good: alſo, not to play the Prince in luſts and riots: laſtly, to retain modeſty in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his fortune, a vertue well becomming the beſt of men, and very pleaſing unto God. The matter is deliver'd in <hi>Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teronomy</hi> thus:
<note place="margin">Deut. 17.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt ſet him King over thee, whom the Lord thy God ſhall chooſe: One from among thy Brethren ſhalt thou ſet King over thee: thou mayeſt not ſet a ſtranger over thee, which is not thy Brother.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:169754:72"/>But he ſhall not multiply horſes to himſelf, nor cauſe the people to return to</hi> Egypt. <hi>For as much as the Lord hath ſaid unto you, ye ſhall henceforth return no more that way. Neither ſhall he mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply Wives to himſelf, that his heart turn not away: neither ſhall he greatly multiply to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſilver and gold. And it ſhall be when he ſitteth upon the throne of his Kingdom, that he ſhall write him a Copy of this Law in a Book, out of that which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prieſts the Levites. And it ſhall be with him, and he ſhall read therein all the dayes of his life: that he may learn to fear the Lord his God, to keep all the words of this Law, and theſe Statutes to do them: That his heart be not lifted up above his Brethren.</hi> Theſe words of the Law are not obſcure, and they
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169754:73"/>ſeem to contain the ſum of that volume, which the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet laid up in the Sanctuary. We ſaid
<note n="*" place="margin">Cap. 8.</note> above, the Jews had ſuch a Common-wealth, which in the Scripture is called a Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kingdom. Whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that their Kings did not only govern in civill affairs, and military, but were Preſidents of Religion and holy Ceremonies. For they were ſacred perſons, to whom Gods Commiſſion and the voice of a Prophet gave Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, honour and authority. Yet as the Over-ſight of Sacred things, the Soveraign power and judgment pertained unto them, ſo the myſtery and charge of the ſame things was of right claimed by the Levites, that is, the High Prieſt, the reſt of the Prieſts, and their aſſiſtants. It was their office, to ſlay the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:169754:73"/>to make expiations, to rehearſe the divine Laws before the people, and to perform other ſervices in the Temple. The Talmudicall writers well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how much the King ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled all, both Prieſts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: which we will relate out of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Halu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha Mela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim,</hi> cap. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Maimonides.</hi> The words are to this effect: <hi>It was a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, that the chief Prieſt ſhould reverence the King, and yield him his place to ſit in, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſtand, when the King came to him. But, the King ſtandeth not in the preſence of the Prieſt, unleſs when he conſults the</hi> U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim <hi>after the ſolemn manner. And, ſuch is the dignity of the King, that even the Prophet himſelf, as oft as he comes into his preſence, bows himſelf down to the earth: as it is written,</hi> Nathan <hi>the Prophet came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:169754:74"/>the King, and, to honour him, fell upon his face to the ground.</hi> Yet more, <hi>David</hi> himſelf, whom the Prophet formerly had anointed King, ſo little feared to take upon him the honour of the High Prieſt, that he put upon himſelf the Ephod, and enquired of the Lord, whether he ſhould purſue the enemy. The place is eminent in the Book of <hi>Samuel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 30. v. 7.</note> perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the late Interpreters, men very learned, but here they ſeem indiligent. Let all men judge that have any skill in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, whether the words tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated by them, <hi>Applicavit ſibi Abiathar amiculum, Davidis cauſa,</hi> ſignify not the ſame I have ſaid, that <hi>David,</hi> having put on the Ephod of <hi>Abiathar,</hi> conſulted the Oracle <hi>[The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Bible reads it,</hi> And <hi>Abia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thar</hi>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:169754:74"/>brought thither the Ephod to <hi>David.</hi> Grotius de Imperio <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>reads it in this ſenſe, Abia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thar</hi> made the Ephod to come near to <hi>David, that as he ſtood before the high Prieſt (which the King only did when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted</hi> Urim) <hi>he might ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſparkling of the prectous ſtones would promiſe him good ſucceſs.</hi> Abiathar <hi>then had the Ephod upon him, not</hi> David. <hi>The</hi> Urim <hi>anſwered.</hi> i. e. <hi>God by the</hi> Urim. vide locum.] But let us give you ſome more of our Collections from the Rabbins. Herein alſo conſiſted an high point of honour,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>im. c.</hi> 2. <hi>in Hal. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l. &amp;</hi> c. 7. <hi>Hal. Beth. Habb.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that the King only, and no man elſe, might ſit in the Court of the Temple, in any place; only the King who was of</hi> Davids <hi>family.</hi> That Court was divided by certain ſpaces, one part for the Prieſts,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:169754:75"/>another aſſigned for the people; Yet the Prieſts cuuld not ſit down, though within their own preſcribed bounds. The Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> had right to ſit:
<note place="margin">Maimon ib.</note> but, <hi>in the midſt of that place which the prophane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people had.</hi> Never did the more ſacred ſpaces of the Court behold any man ſitting, but the King: this being his Prerogative, as if he were nearer to God than the Prieſts themſelves, and a greater Preſident of Religion. And, if we go to other Nations, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, <hi>in the firſt times the ſame perſon, for the moſt part, was both King and Prieſt.</hi> This was no depraved cuſtom, being in uſe, while people fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed nature more incorruptly, and ſaw what was right, ſo much better, by how much nearer they were to the divine originall.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:169754:75"/>But, to ſpeak of the Hebrew Kings, their ſacredneſs depended much upon their being anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. This was proper to them and the high Prieſts, as the <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mud</hi> ſaith, <hi>That anointing ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a divine Majeſty to the Kings, and made them ſacred, and allyed unto God.</hi> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why in thoſe times they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered or reſtored Religion, was not becauſe they were Prophets: (that's a groundleſs and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous opinion, for except <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and perhaps <hi>Saul,</hi> no one of the reſt prophecyed of things to come:) but <hi>Salonion</hi> and <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> and <hi>Ezechiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and others exerciſed power and authority over things divine, becauſe the vertue of the ſacred Ointment had been communicated to them. This Ointment <hi>Moſes</hi> was directed
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169754:76"/>to make of thoſe aromatick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients which
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Hal. Cele Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mik.</hi> c. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Maimonides</hi> deſcribes. And the <hi>Talmud</hi> ſaith, it was uſed for initiation and conſecration untill the times of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſiah,</hi> who hid it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ground in the Temple, in a ſecret place prepared carefully long before by <hi>Salomon,</hi> upon notice of the prophecies, that the Temple ſhould at laſt be thrown down by the Aſſyrians. In the ſame ſecret place (as the Tradition alſo is) the Ark of the Covenant, and <hi>Aarons</hi> red, and the ſtones <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim,</hi> with the reſidue of Manna, were laid up by <hi>Joſiah:</hi> and none of them all was reſtored to the Jews, when upon their return from <hi>Babylon</hi> into their native ſeat, they built the ſecond Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Wherefore, ſince that time the Kings and Prieſts received
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:169754:76"/>not the ſame Majeſty from the myſterious initiation. Nor was the Deity ſo propitious to their ceremonies and ſacred rites, as before The Jews have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb among them, related by
<note n="*" place="margin">In libro Juchaſia.</note> 
                  <hi>Rabbi Zacuth: The fire lay upon the Altar, as a Dog, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the vertue of it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct, after the five things were wanting in the later temple: but in the former, that fire was like a Lyon.</hi> The learned wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter plainly ſaith, the five things were wanting, which even now we ſaid were ſo hidden by <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> that poſterity never found them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:169754:77"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV. Jeroboams <hi>policy to get the Kingdom. The declination and change of Common-wealths.</hi> Scipio<hi>'s moderation. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of common people.</hi> Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria <hi>an imperiall City. Change of Religion a ſecret of State. The diviſion of the ten tribes, and the miſerable effects of it. The Captivity of the I ſraelites, and of the Jews.</hi> Babylon <hi>enlarged by the ſpoils of</hi> Jeruſalem. <hi>The return of the Jews, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Levites.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe unity of the Hebrew na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the frame of that goodly Empire was cleft in two by <hi>Jeroboams</hi> policy, a man no leſs ambitious than valiant. Being commander of the Tribe of <hi>Joſeph</hi> in the War, and put
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169754:77"/>in hope of the Kingdom by the Prophet, rightly conceiving Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are made by Providence, He applyed his vaſt and climing ſpirit to obtain the Dominion. Firſt he attempted the Souldiers faith, endeavouring to draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their affections from <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> to himſelf: but the Plot being diſcovered, to avoid pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment he left his Country, and hid his head in <hi>Egypt.</hi> After the death of <hi>Salomon</hi> he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and met with a conjuncture of affairs very favourable to his great deſigns. The heavy tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, the unjuſt exactions were a fair pretence, which he gladly layd hold on to ſtir up the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people: and ſo brought all into a combuſtion, and became the Author of very great cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, that quickly invaded
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169754:78"/>
                  <hi>Paleſtin.</hi> Verily, ſo it uſually comes to paſs, that no grear Common-wealth hath a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune long continuing at one ſtay. The Hebrews were now come to the hight of their proſperity. All was ſafe and quiet, incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible was the encreaſe of riches, the Kings and Princes near and far off were friends, and no room now was left for their greatneſs to extend it ſelf. Wherefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uncapable of any farther encreaſe, what remained, but that it ſhould according to the Law of fate, decreaſe, and (which is the moſt miſerable condition of humane affairs) decline to the worſe. <hi>Scipio Africanus,</hi> when he purged the City by Sacrifice, being Cenſor, and the Scribe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed to him the ſolemn pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that the Gods would advance the Common-wealth of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:169754:78"/>ſaid, it was great enough already, and deſir'd the Gods only to preſerve it: commanding the prayer, in the publick record, ſhould be thus corrected. The moſt prudent Roman well knowing, that the celeſtiall bounty doth not ſo favour its own gifts, as to make them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies peculiar to any people, feared a viciſſitude and change of fortune, proceeding (as he doubtleſs had in his thoughts) not only from a forein Invader, but from domeſtick cauſes; every State breeding, within her own bowels, diſeaſes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and deſtroy it ſelf. <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> is an example. The moſt flouriſhing City in the world, where <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> two moſt potent and moſt wiſe Kings, had made a deep and ſecure peace, could not long
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169754:79"/>continue quiet. For, <hi>Salomon</hi> being dead, although ſhe had no enemy abroad, ſhe found one at home. <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> of whom I ſpake, a man of a moſt turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſpirit, aroſe; who in ſhort time with better ſucceſs effected the rebellious deſign he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unproſperouſly attempted. An Aſſembly being called, he accuſed the publick State, and the condition of the times, and the Princes doings, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the people: whoſe ears (he knew) are ever open, and glad to hear ill reports of their Superiours. Liberty and other ſpecious names hee pretended, when his ſecret thoughts were, how to enſlave others, and get Dominion to himſelf. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, enflamed by his violent words, fell preſently into ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ways, whereby the moſt
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169754:79"/>antient Kingdoms and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Common-wealths uſually go to ruin, or at leaſt are chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. Forthwith, the Captain of the Rebellion drew off the ten Tribes, whom he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with, from the territories of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and, to ſecure his dominion, and ſettle it, choſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> for his Imperiall City. That his Government might be more firm, he altered many cuſtoms of the Nation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed another worſhip of the deity, a new Religion. For, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up calves to be adored, he renewed the old ſuperſtition, and made Religion, (the cement of Common-wealths) a tye upon the people, to keep them in his obedience, when he could not oblige them by the goodneſs of his cauſe. After which time, the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> drunk
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169754:80"/>with their ſweet abominations, reeled more and more from <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and refuſed (as upon their Gods command) to have any Communion with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof. And now, whatſoever cauſe of hoſtility there happened elſe, the greateſt reaſon alwaies ſeemed that, which was taken from their different Religions. Thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> divers from that of the Jews, the ſeat whereof was at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> And here is the ſpring of all the calamities that came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Hebrews. For, being weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by themſelves, and having drawn much blood from one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, they were made a prey to forein Nations, who before were invincible againſt all the world. Now <hi>Suſac</hi> the Egyptian ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the holy City and the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169754:80"/>and by way of diſgrace ſet Pillars in ſeverall places, upon which were carved ('tis a ſha me to ſpeak) the ſecrets of Women. A fact, which <hi>Herodotus,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes unto <hi>Seſoſtris,</hi> by miſtake of the name, as <hi>Flavius</hi> hath rightly judged. A bitter cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, this: but the things which a long time after were ſuffered both by the Jews and Iſraelites, were far more grievous. And firſt by <hi>Salmanaſſar</hi> the Aſſyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, was quite deſtroy'd and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrown, the Empire of the ten Tribes. The whole Nation, being carried into <hi>Media</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> gave place to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Hittites, whom <hi>Eſarhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> ſoon after ſent out of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> into <hi>Paleſtin</hi> to inhabit the Land of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> So do Kings, according to their pleaſure, uſe to tranſlate Nations, like Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169754:81"/>which Shepheards drive ſometimes into their Winter, ſometimes into their Summer paſture. For by this means peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are tamed and ſoftned, and they that dare any thing at home, are held under quiet ſubjection in a ſtrange Land. Never had the Iſraelites, after that time, the happineſs to return into their own Country, or to repair the ruins of their Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. They had ſo highly offended God by their impious Idolatry, that no length of time, nor revolution of ages, could pacify his wrath. The Iſraelites being thus gone into their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall exile, the Jews remained to receive their due puniſhment likewiſe. Which was inflicted on them as ſurely, though more ſlowly. In the reign of <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah, Nebuchodonozor</hi> with a
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:169754:81"/>mighty army ſubdued <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Syria:</hi> and burnt to aſhes the City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, a place of infinite opulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. In which time, Himſelf, upon news of <hi>Nabolaſſars</hi> death, haſtning home to take poſſeſſion of the Kingdom, left Commiſſion with his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to bring away the Jews to <hi>Babylon</hi> and the places there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about. There he aſſigned them their ſeats, and Fields, in the culture whereof this new Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny might ſpend their time and get their living. Venerable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of antiquity remain of <hi>Beroſus</hi> Annals, wherein 'tis written, that <hi>Nebuchodonozor,</hi> out of the ſpoils brought thence, built a Temple to <hi>Belus,</hi> enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Babylon</hi> according to the Majeſty of his Empire, and girt it with Walls of Brick: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:169754:82"/>made Gardens in the Air, and pendent Woods in favour of his Wife, who having been bred in the mountainous parts of <hi>Media,</hi> delighted in the proſpect of Woods growing in high places. Whence appears the vanity of that which the Grecians have delivered with great conſent, that <hi>Semiramis</hi> raiſed thoſe admired works. For they are confuted by an Author in <hi>Flavius</hi> beyond all exception; namely <hi>Beroſus</hi> the Chaldean, who (as all men have believed) is moſt antient, and with very great Religion and truth hath conſecrated the affairs of his own Nation to eternall memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But the Jews were not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo grievouſly by the hand of God, nor ſo long as the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites. They lived in a gentle and eaſy exile, as in a Country
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:169754:82"/>of their own: and, after ſeventy years were gone about, they were reſtor'd to <hi>Paleſtin,</hi> rebuilt their City and Temple, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed their Common-wealth again. Here now was the ſtate of things much different from what it was before. For, the Empire which before was in the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> was now u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped by the Levits, after a various manner. Theſe men, having gotten into their hands the Supreme Power, advanced the Common-wealth indeed to the height of riches and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but, while they contend among themſelves for power and honour, they trod under foot both divine and humane things. So little of piety and modeſty did the moſt ſacred name of Religion give to them, whom God had ſelected for
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:169754:83"/>himſelf, out of all the reſt, and ſeparated ſo long ago, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the holy offices and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, they ſhould lead their lives, far from ambition and vain glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>The Prieſts have the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Their evill behaviour. Of the ſons of</hi> Eliſab. <hi>The tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of</hi> Garizin <hi>built. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs of</hi> Onias. <hi>The vertue of</hi> Matthias, <hi>and of</hi> Judas Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabaeus. Alcimus <hi>his outrage.</hi> Judea <hi>again under Kings. Of</hi> Herod, <hi>his cruelty, and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OF the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the reſtauration of the City and Temple, firſt the High
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:169754:83"/>Prieſts ruled all, without aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Title of Prince or King. Theſe enjoyed themſelves, or diſpoſed of to others, all favour, wealth and power: the reſt were Plebeians, without honour, without authority. Therefore, they that were but Levites were competitors, for ſo great a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment; and uſed all endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, ſome by force, ſome by fraud and fallacies, few by the true way, to attain unto it. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be imagined more diſhonourable, than what the two Sons of the high Prieſt <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſab</hi> committed after their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's death. For both Jeſus, by the help of a barbarous Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, went about wickedly to deprive his Brother <hi>Jannes</hi> of the high Prieſthood, which he had received according to the Law: and <hi>Jannes,</hi> to retain his right,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:169754:84"/>became guilty of a greater wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs; for he ſlew the ſame Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus with his own hand, in the temple of God, and ſprinkled the altars with his Brothers Blood. <hi>Jannes</hi> not long after had for his ſucceſſor <hi>Jaddus;</hi> Whoſe Pontificate likewiſe his Brother <hi>Manaſſes</hi> devoured in his hopes: but having married, againſt the Law, a ſtrange Woman, the Daughter of <hi>Sanballet,</hi> whence aroſe a tumult amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he quickly perceived a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity lying upon him, either to loſe his affinity with ſo potent a Father-law, or elſe relinquiſh his hopes of the Prieſt-hood. Here, upon long deliberatioa with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, at laſt, having communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated his Counſels to his Father-in-Law, he conceived a notable enterprize, which all poſterity talks of, none approves. For
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:169754:84"/>he reſolved to erect a Temple in <hi>Garizin,</hi> the higheſt mountain of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and ſhortly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved power to doe ſo, from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> by the mediation of <hi>Sanballet.</hi> Thus he, that was not capable of the moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable office at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had violated the Law, became High-Prieſt, as he could, in another place, and in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it thought himſelf in Heaven. See the heart of a moſt wicked man, in whom you may doubt whether his ambition or impiety were the greater. Yet was this but a ſmall thing, in compariſon of what <hi>Onias</hi> the fourth did, out of a deſire of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. Being made High-Prieſt, and ſeeing himſelf too weak for <hi>Jaſons</hi> faction, to get the favour of <hi>Antiochus Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes,</hi>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:169754:85"/>whoſe protection he nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he forſwore the Moſaic Laws, and inſtead of them ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Religions and rites of the Grecians. And more, that he might not bear in his Body the marks of Circumciſion, he renewed his fore-skin by Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall Art, and perſwaded all his people to do the like. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> the High-Prieſt being his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, impiouſly perverted all the inſtitutions of the Jews. And now nothing of the ſound and the antient cuſtoms remained when <hi>Matthias</hi> the <hi>Haſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naean,</hi> the great reſtorer of the State, having taken up Arms, rendred to the Jews their Laws, and received the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth under his Rule, with the title of Prince. Being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:169754:85"/>to him ſucceeded <hi>Judas</hi> in the Principality, the ſame that is called <hi>Maccabaeus.</hi> Yet was there great power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the High-Prieſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Antiochus Eupator</hi> after that time, cunningly having got entrance into <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when he diſtruſted <hi>Onias,</hi> upon whom he ſaw the people and the State affairs depended much, placed <hi>Alcimus</hi> in his room. But he, being gotten into the holy chair, was more depraved than his Predeceſſor; for he went over to King <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Son of <hi>Seleucus,</hi> with criminations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Judas,</hi> whoſe principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity he could not away with. Impiety can be never quiet, nor content with a ſingle tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Wherefore hee brought againſt his own Country the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:169754:86"/>Kings Lieutenant <hi>Bacohides,</hi> with an Army; and after his return to the King without effecting the work, he encreaſed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies left by <hi>Bacchides,</hi> by the concourſe of wicked men. From every place were gathered unto <hi>Alcimus,</hi> Murderers, Sacrilegious Perſons, Adulterers; whom their guilty conſciences would not ſuffer to reſt at home: and he engaged them all to do him ſervice, by fair words and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull pay. At the laſt, this gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Prieſt, to adde more unto his glorious impiety, prepared to throw down the Walls of the Sanctuary raiſed by the Prophets and the Haſidaeans; But in the midſt of his deſign death cut him off, and in his place the people conſtituted, in the moſt ſacred office, their Prince
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:169754:86"/>
                  <hi>Judas;</hi> the firſt of all the Jews that joynd the Miter and the Crown together, and was both Prince and Prieſt. The ſame was done, after him, by <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, Simon</hi> and <hi>Jannes:</hi> untill <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> the name of Prince being laid aſide, took upon him the title of King. And ſo, in the end, long after the death of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dekiah,</hi> Kings again ruled over <hi>Judaea,</hi> but they were of the Tribe of <hi>Levi;</hi> the laſt of whom was <hi>Antigonus. Antigonus</hi> being expelled and ſlain, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> held the Scepter, which he had before received from the Romans: a man, not indeed deſcended of the Royall family, no nor of the Sacerdotall, but one of <hi>Idumaea,</hi> an inſititious Jew or Proſelyte; for the Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeans were not truly Jews, but
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:169754:87"/>only accounted and called ſo, ſince the time that <hi>Hircanus</hi> forced them to ſubmit to the rites and ceremonies of the true God, when before they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt, I know not what good, <hi>Goſan,</hi> whoſe rites were kept by the <hi>Coſtobari,</hi> a noble family in that Country. Famous was that prophecy of <hi>Sameas,</hi> who had long ſince foretold, that <hi>Herod</hi> ſhould bee given the Jews for a King, but to be a Plague unto them. Even ſo it came to paſs. This Idumaean preſently put to death <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus</hi> the High-Prieſt, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry young; and after him <hi>Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus,</hi> allured out of <hi>Parthia;</hi> and after him, whatſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained of the Haſmonaean bloud, he extinguiſhed, and left not any branch of the old ſtock.
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:169754:87"/>Nor did the ſeventy Elders, the Aſſeſſors of the Great Councill Sannedrin, ſpeed better. Thus all being remov'd out of the way, who might create him either fear or danger, <hi>Herod</hi> grew up to his height, and the greatneſs of his power gave him boldneſs to break forth into great licence; for he altered the old cuſtoms of the Jews, and brought in new, and did many things contrary to the Laws. Whereof let us hear <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſpeaking thus: <hi>The antient diſcipline, untainted before, he weakned with Innovations: whence, in our following times, we have had no ſmall harm; for all thoſe things, whereby the multitude was heretofore led unto piety, are now neglected and deſpiſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:169754:88"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>Of Meſſias, King of the Jews and all Nations. The everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting throne is his. A word in</hi> Eſay <hi>written myſtically.</hi> Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams <hi>prophecy in the ſenſe of the Jews. The ſingular nature of Meſſia's Kingdom. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehender of</hi> Maimonides <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured.</hi> Ezekiels <hi>obſcure viſion, not to be curiouſly ſearched.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd in this manner, after the Jews return out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> they were in poſſeſſion of the Empire that had no right unto it; firſt the High-Prieſts, then the Haſmonaean Princes, being alſo Levites, then Kings of the ſame tribe, and laſtly <hi>Herod</hi> the Idumaean; He, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom was born Meſſias,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:169754:88"/>the King of Kings, a branch of <hi>Davids</hi> family. To him alone muſt be referr'd that promiſe God made to <hi>David,</hi> that his throne ſhould bee everlaſting, and his ſeed ſhould ſit therein. Certainly, it is not ſpoken of <hi>Salomon,</hi> nor of any other of his race; for, the kingdom once loſt, they never recover'd after the Babylonian exile. Wherefore, unleſs wee will (which were great impiety) make the promiſe of God vain and falſe, we muſt underſtand that Son of <hi>David</hi> to bee the Meſſias, our Redeemer, of whom the Angel hath pronounced that which is written in St. Luke: <hi>Of his Kingdom there ſhall be no end.</hi> The words are taken out of the ninth of <hi>Eſaiah,</hi> where <hi>Rabbi Jarchi</hi> notes: <hi>It was
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:169754:89"/>ſubtilly diſputed by the Scribes, why in the midſt of a word, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to cuſtom, the letter</hi> Mem <hi>is cloſed.</hi> A doubt not to be contemned. Thereby is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied (as the Talmudiſts are of opinion) ſome great myſtery, not opened promiſcuouſly unto all, but cloſe and reſerved. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the Oracles in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, concerning the greateſt King Meſſias, the Jews think none ſo worthy of admiration, as that which <hi>Balaam</hi> uttered by divine inſtinct. <hi>Num.</hi> 24. But the ſame Interpreters, looking narrowly into the Prophets meaning, ſagely found, the words are not all ſpoken of one King: but the oracle is ſo to be divided, that part may belong to <hi>David,</hi> who firſt of <hi>Juda</hi>'s race poſſeſt the Kingdom, the reſt to the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:169754:89"/>Meſſias, the laſt King indeed of the ſame race, but greater and more potent than all the other. <hi>Maimonides</hi> in the end of his <hi>Miſna</hi> hath handled this exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And the ſame excellent Maſter there refutes thoſe, that exſpect in the Kingdom of <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> another face of nature, and a new courſe of things going on perpetually. For, ſaith he, they underſtood not the words of <hi>Eſaiah</hi> in the 12. Chapter. The dark ſayings whereof doe ſignifie, that all pious and good men ſhall have ſuch quietneſs in the midſt of the wicked, that they need not fear. Nor hath <hi>Rabbi Abraham</hi> the Son of <hi>David</hi> any juſt reaſon to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend <hi>Maimonides</hi> for this: whoſe other reprehenſions too, for the moſt part, are more
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:169754:90"/>ſharp than ſolid, they make a ſhew of reaſon, but, when they are examined, come to nothing. As oft as I ſurvey the ſacred pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the rites and Religious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities, deſcribed by the moſt holy Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in the laſt part of his Book, I conſider with my ſelf, what they mean, or whither they are to be referr'd. So different are they from <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> precepts, and the Jewiſh cuſtoms, as themſelves confeſs. What opinion is to be had of them, the
<note n="*" place="margin">In tract. Menachoth.</note> 
                  <hi>Talmud</hi> hath reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Maimonides</hi> hath in brief expreſſed: <hi>All manner of offerings, ſpoken of in</hi> Ezekiel, <hi>and whatſoever is there written of the number of Sacrifices, and of the order of divine worſhip, are nothing elſe but the pacific ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, which have not been
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:169754:90"/>uſed in former ages by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but the Prophet ſhews, how they ſhall be performed at the dedication of the new Altar, in the times of Meſſias, when the third Temple ſhall be built.</hi> This is no Jewiſh dream, nor Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudicall conceit, but a certain Truth. The Prophet hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed another Temple, which ſhould be in Meſſia's reign, and other ſacred rites: and hath meaſured the ſtructure of the Temple, the Courts, the Gates, and the reſt, by an accurate rule of the work. The form of it, ſay the Jews, is not fully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, but <hi>Ezra,</hi> when he built the ſecond Temple after the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of <hi>Salomons,</hi> followed alſo the deſcription of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> third Temple, ſo far as the capacity of the moſt holy man could
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:169754:91"/>reach, in ſo obſcure and perplext a matter. This we learn from the Prince of Rabbins in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Hal. Beth. Hab.</hi> c. 1.</note> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place. Nevertheleſs, it is no little blindneſs in the Jews, that they hope for ſuch a Temple to be built by the Meſſias, which may be ſeen with the eyes, and approached with the feet. We that are born in Meſſia's Kingdom know full well, 'tis otherwiſe. All the Prophets words, of the meaſure of the buildings, and the parts, have another more ſecret ſenſe; but what that ſenſe is, and how the words are to be explained, is hard to ſay. For my part, with <hi>Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophane</hi> in <hi>Varro, I would have every man to ſet down what he thinketh, not what he will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert; for man may have an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſuch things, God alone
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:169754:91"/>knows them certainly.</hi> Truly the Jews when they mention ſome pieces of the Bible, the reading whereof is interdicted youth, put the end of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy in that rank. And not without cauſe. For the whole diſcourſe is more obſcure than <hi>Plato</hi>'s number. Let them all, who would ſeem the greateſt proficients in divine wiſdom, call hither their induſtry: they will ſweat enough, before they open the leaſt of the things laid up in thoſe leaves. The beſt interpreter can but give a handſom conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture at the utmoſt, and when all is done we muſt remain unreſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. This is certain, that theſe, and ſome other things of like kind, are ſuch, as the moſt high God hath ſet above the reach of humane wit; for, though in this
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:169754:92"/>light of the Goſpell, great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs hath been made into ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yet ſomewhat is ſtill left for admiration. Wherefore to go farther into theſe ſecrets, than the bounds preſcribed to us by the Holy Spirit, would be a very unwiſe adventure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>The State of the Jews after Meſſia</hi>'s <hi>comming. Of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution yet exſpected. The dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of that Nation even at this day. How much our Religion ows to the Jews. The Scripture not corrupted by them. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorites dilligence and fidelity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT was the pleaſure of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall God, that the Jews ſhould be called a Royall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:169754:92"/>and a choſen Generation, and that his ſacred rites and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies ſhould be embraced by them alone, untill the day ſhined forth, that ſhewed the Meſſias to the world. From that time, the Son of God ordained, that the celeſtiall benefits, long confined unto one Nation, ſhould be common to all; the Tydings whereof, ſent abroad far and wide, profited believers only. Here we muſt admire at the ſtrange converſion of things. For the great Author of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who had left his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly throne to relieve the miſeries of men, was entertained by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Nations with joy and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: but the Jews, to whom more than one Prophet had ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified both the place and time of his coming, knew him not,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:169754:93"/>when he was come and preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf amongſt them. So great a dulneſs had ſeized on them. Their eyes were blind, when their thoughts were on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters and refuſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what was ſet before them in the midſt. Hereupon they were abdicated and caſt off by God, and even to this day <hi>they eat Pottage, and deplore their loſt birth-right.</hi> Their crime is engraven in the <hi>Hardeſt Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jeremy</hi> the Prophet. Nor did they deprecate their puniſhment, but called it to themſelves ſaying. <hi>His blood be upon us, and upon our Children.</hi> Very memorable is that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> writeth to the Romans:
<note place="margin">Rom. 11. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>I would not have you ignorant of this myſtery, that hardneſs, in part, hath happened unto</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:169754:93"/>
                  <hi>untill the fulneſs of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles be come in.</hi> Certainly there will come a time, when the Jews ſhall be reduced into the right path, who do now wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der miſerably through ignorance of the way. The Suns of all days are not yet gone down: their light ſhall once again break forth unto them: and though they are fallen, they are not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len away for ever. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> alſo hath publiſhed ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies in favour of them. Ch. 36. The Prophet faith, a new heart ſhall be given them from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and a better underſtanding ſhall dwell in their breaſt. Then ſhall the veil be taken off, which <hi>Moſes</hi> put upon his face; for they ſhall convert themſelves unto God, who ſuffered them to live in darkneſs, and in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:169754:94"/>of the greateſt matters, that at laſt he might take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſhew his old loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And on this wiſe do we commodiouſly interpret theſe words of <hi>Paul:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>When</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be turned to the Lord; the veil ſhall be taken away:</hi> a very obſcure place to many, and wherein ſome have taken much pains. The thing of which we ſpeak, is of ſuch conſequence, that juſtly we cannot henceforth be altogether averſe from the Jews, as if they were given up to publick hatred, when as yet ſo great hopes are remaining for them. And truly S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth them reverence, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tols them with high praiſe, even while they are in errour.
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>To whom</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>pertaineth the adoption, and the glory, and the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:169754:94"/>Covenants, and the giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God, and the promiſes: Whoſe are the Fathers, and of whom concerning the fleſh Chriſt came.</hi> What Nobility could be greater? So many Patriarchs, and Prophets, and Kings, they number among their forefathers; and ſo many brave men, and men of divine vertue, whoſe names are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated in Heaven. I confeſs, all the Jews at this day are of a baſe and illiberall diſpoſition; and, if you look upon their courſe of life, you can hardly find any thing worthy of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and erected ſpirits: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we marvell at the cauſe hereof. For theſe things goe in a round, and as the times are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo are mens manners. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, the ſame day that depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:169754:95"/>them of the fair light of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and ſtruck the Scepter out of their hands, did alſo ſo abate the edge of their ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirits, that they have no more vigor now, nor keeneſs in them. Servitude dwarfs the mind, and enchains the ſpirit, and choaks all the ſeeds of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity. What high thoughts can they poſſibly have, who, for ſo many years, through the whole world, have been wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed out with ſo great ſcorn and contumely? whom Children, in contempt, have pulled by the ſleeve, and men by the beard? laſtly, upon whom the fury of all the <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſpent it ſelf. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> diſtributed their young men, ſending them as it were for Souldiers, into the Provinces of unwholeſome air. The air of
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:169754:95"/>
                  <hi>Sardinea</hi> was very peſtilent, Thither are four thouſand com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded away, to meet an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death. <hi>Titus</hi> caſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as many to the beaſts, when hee ſet forth ſhews at <hi>Berytum</hi> and <hi>Caeſarea. Trajan</hi> himſelf, the mildeſt of all the Princes, decreed they ſhould not read the Law; ſo did other Emperors after him at ſeverall times. This was the greateſt of afflictions, and by <hi>Rabbi Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuth</hi> is numbred among the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions: <hi>They decreed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a perſecution, that the Jews ſhould not read the Law.</hi> But theſe things were done by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans: Let us, who are joyned to them with a cloſer bond, ſhew them more favour, having this communion with them, to hear the commands of one and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:169754:96"/>the ſame God. Truly S. <hi>Paul</hi> deſires to lay down his life for them, ſo fervent is his charity to the Nation. And it is his ſaying,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.16.</note> 
                  <hi>If the firſt fruits bee holy, the lump is alſo holy: and if the root be holy, ſo are the branches.</hi> I will not now am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly celebrate their praiſes: for wee abhor from nothing more; than ſuch Vanity. Yet, as to theſe later times, the truth is, if we caſt up the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count rightly, out Religion is much endebted to that people. For who are they but the Jews, that have preſerved for us the ſacred volumes of the Bible ſafe and ſound? How many <hi>Erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>'s had ſtoln into the Holy Scriptures, had the cuſtody thereof been committed only to ſuch as <hi>Lactantius, Auſtin,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:169754:96"/>Gregory, Chryſoſtom,</hi> moſt holy men indeed, but unskilfull of the Hebrew tongue? Amongſt all the Greek and Latine Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that governed the antient Church, <hi>Origen,</hi> and (to ſpeak the moſt) <hi>Jerom</hi> were the only Hebricians: the reſt had not learned ſo much as the very Letters; Wherefore if the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs of Tranſcribers had made default, they were not the men that could make amends. But this was all the Jews only ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and their ſole care, to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets, and the other holy writings, from the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of time. This is their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per praiſe: wherein no other Nation c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>imeth any ſhare. There is an eminent place in <hi>Rabbi Abraham</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In libre Juchaſin:</note> of <hi>Salman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:169754:97"/>whence we learn. That all the Copies of the Bible were amended according to a certain Book of venerable antiquity, written long before by the hand of <hi>Rabbi Hillel,</hi> High-Prieſt of the Jews, who came from <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> into <hi>Syria</hi> ſixty years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Nativity of our Lord God Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>In the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of</hi> Leon (ſaith he) <hi>they found the Bible written by</hi> Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi Hillel, <hi>and by it corrected all their Copies; part of it I ſaw, which was ſold in</hi> Afric, <hi>and was written</hi> 900. <hi>years before my time.</hi> Kimhi <hi>in his Grammar ſaith, the Pentateuch was at the City of</hi> Toledo. At that time therefore the Jews were the only Correctors to keep the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of the Bible pure. Indeed, it had been eaſy for them, to
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:169754:97"/>alter and corrupt thoſe places, which ſeemed to condemn their follies, when the Chriſtians un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood ſcarce three words of Hebrew: but piety with-ſtood, and Religion would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to change what was ſacred. Nevertheleſs, ſome have charged them with unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in deſcribing much of the text; but theſe men have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready had ſufficient anſwer from learned
<note n="*" place="margin">8. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plan. Eſaiae.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Origen.</hi> As for me, when I conſider the unwearyed dilligence and infinite pains of the <hi>Maſorites,</hi> I do even ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed; for, having reviſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately, and compared all the parts of the Hebrew Bible, they ſigned them with certain notes. This was done after the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſecond Temple, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year 436. It was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:169754:98"/>by them, not only how many Verſes and words, but alſo how many Letters every Book contained. Wherefore, that afterward, when extreme barbatiſm oppreſt the world, no tittle of that moſt excellent Book was loſt, is a benefit we ow to them. Not without cauſe have the Rabbins ſaid, <hi>The</hi> Maſora <hi>is as it were the wall and the hedge of the Law.</hi> In <hi>Rabbi Zacuth</hi> above cited, are Judaicall trifles, whereby forſooth it is concluded, that the Accents and the Points were extant in the time of <hi>Ezra;</hi> which I therefore mention, that it may be added to the reſt of thoſe vain arguments alleged by ſome, who in our time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them to be the invention of the Maſorites. And in the ſame
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:169754:98"/>Rabbies Book, by the ſame proof is the Targum of <hi>Onke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los</hi> referd to <hi>Ezra</hi>'s age. Which, although it be falſe, and eaſily diſcovers how little worth the other is, yet will find ſome to defend it, the rather, that the other may not fall. Many are ſo obſtinately given, they care not what they ſay, if it may but ſerve to maintain the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they have once embraced. That the reading of the holy Scripture is not uncertain, and ſubject to any more variation, wee thankfully acknowledge the care and pains of the Jews, who lived in the later times, after the deſtruction of the ſecond Temple: For, when they were fallen from their great and wealthy State, they made it their buſineſs, amidſt
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:169754:99"/>their extreme calamity, to ſave out of the common Shipwrack this one Cheſt of ineſtimable value. And this is that we love them for; the reſt deſerve our compaſſion: For they read the Tittles, and Letters, and Books, but they read them only, not regarding nor ſeeking the true and ſacred ſenſe. So that, the ſaying of their own well agrees unto themſelves: <hi>They make that which is fundamentall, a leſſer matter; and the leſſer matter, fundamentall.</hi> And, which is worſt of all, they are not ſenſible of their Childiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and folly; for, whereas all their infelicity conſiſteth in their ignorance of the divine Law, they complain of the loſs of their Country, and of the Kingdom taken from them,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:169754:99"/>and of the like things: whoſe poſſeſſion makes no man hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and whoſe loſs makes no man miſerable. <hi>Seneca</hi> tels us of his Wifes fool, <hi>Harpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte,</hi> that having on the ſodain loſt her ſight, <hi>ſhe knew not ſhe was blind, and often requeſted her keeper to bring her to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther houſe, for her own was dark.</hi> The Jews are in the ſame caſe. They carry about in their own breaſt the cauſe of all their miſery: and ſuppoſe, by ſome divine favour, they ſhould recover <hi>Canaan,</hi> they would change their climat, not their mind. Whitherſoever they turn themſelves, their night goes along too, and overſhadows them: nor ſhall it be diſpelled, before they
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:169754:100"/>have throughly ſmarted for their ingratitude, and their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy, and the hardneſs of their hearts.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edm. Calamy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table">
            <pb facs="tcp:169754:100"/>
            <head>THE Table Alphabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>R. ABraham. 155</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Acheians.</hi> 85</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Agrarian Law.</hi> 13 17, 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Agriculture.</hi> 20, 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Agrippa's offence.</hi> 50</item>
               <item>Alcimus <hi>High-Prieſt.</hi> 147</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>His impiety.</hi> 148</item>
               <item>Alexander <hi>M. his favour to the Jews.</hi> 27</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:101"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alterations whence.</hi> 18</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ambition.</hi> 141</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anointing of Kings.</hi> 127</item>
               <item>Antigonns <hi>King.</hi> 149</item>
               <item>Antiochus Epiphanes. 146</item>
               <item>Apion cymbalum mundi. 3</item>
               <item>Apollonius Scotus <hi>praiſed.</hi> 70</item>
               <item>Ariſtobulus <hi>King.</hi> 149</item>
               <item>Ariſtotle<hi>'s opinion of the Jews.</hi> 29, 30</item>
               <item>Ariſt. <hi>cited</hi> 5, 8, 31, 119</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Arms of nature.</hi> 15</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Artificers, none among the Jews.</hi> 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Avarice, the hurt of it.</hi> 17</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> 1, 70, 74, 112, 114</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>BAbylon <hi>enlarged by</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buch. 139</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Babylonian Jews.</hi> 62. <hi>Had not the Scepter.</hi> 69</item>
               <item>Balaam's <hi>prophecy expounded.</hi> 154</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:101"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beginning of the Heb. Com.</hi> 59</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Benefit of the Jubily.</hi> 14</item>
               <item>Beroſus <hi>Annals.</hi> 139</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bible, ſome parts not to be read by Youth.</hi> 159. <hi>Forbidden the Jews by</hi> Trajan. 167 <hi>Not corrupted by the Jews</hi> 168</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Buriall of the dead.</hi> 55</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>CAbala. 105</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Capitall offenders.</hi> 110</item>
               <item>Caſaubons exercit. 73. <hi>His praiſe.</hi> 74. <hi>His errour.</hi> 85</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Calendar corrected.</hi> 112</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Captivtty.</hi> 137</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Change of Laws.</hi> 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>City-life.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cities of refuge.</hi> 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>City, what.</hi> 110</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colonies.</hi> 12</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Commands, three to be fulfild
<pb facs="tcp:169754:102"/>in</hi> Paleſtin. 115</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>ommon-wealth founded by</hi> Moſes. 2. <hi>When full of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> 18. <hi>The beſt.</hi> 31. <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixt to</hi> Paleſtin. 61</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſecration of Cities.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Councils of the Jews.</hi> 98, 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Country bred gollant men.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Court of the Temple.</hi> 125</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>DAvids <hi>Scepter.</hi> 91. <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting throne.</hi> 153</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Day of expiation.</hi> 16</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Defection of the ten Tribes.</hi> 136</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Deformity.</hi> 104</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Deſolation of</hi> Jeruſalem. 56, 93</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dominion ſecured by change.</hi> 113</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>EGyptians, their, idle life.</hi> 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elders.</hi> 107</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:102"/>
               <item>Eliſab's <hi>Sons.</hi> 142</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ephod.</hi> 124</item>
               <item>Ephorus <hi>his errour.</hi> 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Equality.</hi> 12</item>
               <item>Euſebius <hi>confuted.</hi> 74, 82</item>
               <item>Ezekiels <hi>obſcure prophecy.</hi> 156</item>
               <item>Ezra. 157</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FAthers errour.</hi> 72. <hi>Unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the Hebrew text.</hi> 168</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Field laid to field.</hi> 20</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fire on the Altaer.</hi> 129</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fortification.</hi> 53</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>GAbinius <hi>abates the power of</hi> Sanhedrin. 113</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gardons and Woods in</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. 140</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>God, the ruler of the Heb. Com.</hi> 6. <hi>Why angry at the deſire of a King.</hi> 117</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:103"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Goſpell common to all Nations.</hi> 161</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grecians Law-givers. Their ignorance of the Jews.</hi> 29</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>HAſmoneans.</hi> 79</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hebrews, why hated by the Egyptians</hi> 34</item>
               <item>Hecateus <hi>praiſed.</hi> 10</item>
               <item>Herod <hi>King.</hi> 149. <hi>His cruelty.</hi> 150</item>
               <item>Herodotus <hi>errour.</hi> 137</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>High Prieſt.</hi> 104</item>
               <item>Hillel. 101, 111.</item>
               <item>Hircanus. 150</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Holy of Holies.</hi> 50</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Holy ointment hid and loſt with other things.</hi> 128</item>
               <item>Homer <hi>hath not the name of Laws.</hi> 3</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Houſes in Cities redeemed.</hi> 47</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:103"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Husbandmen of</hi> Egypt <hi>lazy</hi> 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Husbandry praiſed.</hi> 22</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>JAcobs <hi>prophecy.</hi> 64</item>
               <item>Jarchi. 153</item>
               <item>Jeroboam. 83. <hi>His policy.</hi> 130. <hi>Turbulent.</hi> 134.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Idolatry puniſhed.</hi> 138</item>
               <item>Idumaeans. 150</item>
               <item>Jeruſalems <hi>ſarstity.</hi> 48. <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege.</hi> 54. <hi>The head City.</hi> 55 <hi>Her fall.</hi> 56</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jews had no commerce with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations.</hi> 28. <hi>Spred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</hi> 88. <hi>Knew not their Meſſias.</hi> 161. <hi>Caſt off.</hi> 162 <hi>Not without hope.</hi> 163. <hi>Their dignity.</hi> 164. <hi>Their baſeneſs.</hi> 165. <hi>Our relation to them.</hi> 167. <hi>Our debt to them.</hi> 168</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Imperiall dignity.</hi> 64</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Impiety never quiet.</hi> 147</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:104"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Impoſition of hands.</hi> 100</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Joſephus againſt</hi> Apion <hi>prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> 3. Joſ. <hi>cited.</hi> 27, 50, 87, 151. <hi>His errour.</hi> 120</item>
               <item>Joſhua <hi>Captain Generall.</hi> 96</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jubily, the benefit of it</hi> 14. <hi>the</hi> 49 <hi>year.</hi> 41. <hi>not kept after the captivity.</hi> 41</item>
               <item>Judas Maccabaeus. 147 <hi>Prince and Prieſt.</hi> 149</item>
               <item>Juda<hi>'s Scepter.</hi> 77</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Judges of</hi> Paleſtin <hi>and</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. 68</item>
               <item>Juvenal <hi>cited.</hi> 36</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>KEepers of the Laws.</hi> 7</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kings.</hi> 97</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>King created.</hi> 116. <hi>Qualities of a King.</hi> 118. <hi>Rules for him.</hi> 120. <hi>Preſidents of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> 122. <hi>Dignity.</hi> 123 <hi>King and Prieſt.</hi> 126. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed.</hi> 127</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:104"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kingdom of the Levites.</hi> 149</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Meſſias.</hi> 155</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>LAelius <hi>his wiſdom.</hi> 19</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Law of Jubily.</hi> 23</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Laws, none written before</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. 4. <hi>Impartiall.</hi> 8. Stolo<hi>'s Law.</hi> 18</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Law-givers, their honour.</hi> 2 <hi>The Grecian.</hi> 3</item>
               <item>Levi <hi>and</hi> Benjamin <hi>called Jews.</hi> 85</item>
               <item>Levites <hi>portion.</hi> 46. <hi>Office.</hi> 122 <hi>Reign.</hi> 141</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Liberty pretended, to enſlave,</hi> 134</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>MAgiſtrates:</hi> 106</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Majeſty of the Empire.</hi> 76. <hi>In the people of</hi> Rome. 79</item>
               <item>Maimonides <hi>praiſed.</hi> 13. <hi>Cited.</hi> 16, 25, 41, 49, 61, 64, 68, 101, 102, 108, 115, 155</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:105"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Manſlanghter expiated.</hi> 111</item>
               <item>Manaſſes <hi>High-Prieſt.</hi> 144</item>
               <item>Matthias <hi>the Haſmonean.</hi> 146</item>
               <item>Maſorites <hi>diligence and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> 169</item>
               <item>Mem clauſum. 154</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Merchants.</hi> 30</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meſſias.</hi> 93, 153. <hi>Reign.</hi> 157</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Modeſty in opinion.</hi> 158</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Monarchs, the Judges and Dictators ſo ſtiled.</hi> 96</item>
               <item>Moſes, <hi>the firſt Law-giver.</hi> 2 <hi>More than man.</hi> 7. <hi>The ſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his Law.</hi> 8</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N.</head>
               <item>NEbuchadonozor. 139</item>
               <item>Nero <hi>petition'd by the Jews.</hi> 50</item>
               <item>Nilus <hi>fruitfull.</hi> 39</item>
               <item>Noahs <hi>ſeven precepts.</hi> 5</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>ORdinances of the Jews.</hi> 9</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Opificers illiberall.</hi> 33</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:105"/>
               <item>Onias <hi>High-Prieſt.</hi> 145. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed his fore-skin.</hi> 146</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>PAleſtin. 9. <hi>Fruitfulneſs thereof.</hi> 11, 43. <hi>Divided by</hi> Joſhua. 16</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paſtorall life.</hi> 20</item>
               <item>Paul <hi>interpreted.</hi> 164. <hi>His charity to the Jews.</hi> 168</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peace of</hi> Jeruſalem. 133</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peace loſt by appropriating what was common.</hi> 12</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perſonage goodly.</hi> 119</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perſecution of the Jews.</hi> 167</item>
               <item>Pharaohs <hi>policy.</hi> 37</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plebeians ſingle and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction.</hi> 106</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peoples Majeſty.</hi> 78. <hi>Jealous of Superiors.</hi> 134</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Poſſeſsions too ample.</hi> 17</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Prieſtly kingdom.</hi> 122</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Princes made by providence.</hi> 131</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:106"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Progreſs into ſcience.</hi> 160</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Prophecies.</hi> 92</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Prophets not periſh out of</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. 105</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>QUeſtion of</hi> Juda<hi>'s ſcepter diſcuſſed.</hi> 71</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quiet of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths.</hi> 132</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>REaſon and prudence.</hi> 5</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Redemption of Land.</hi> 15 <hi>Of houſes.</hi> 47</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Refuge.</hi> 57</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Religion keeps in awe.</hi> 9. <hi>The ſoul of the Common-wealth.</hi> 65. <hi>The cement.</hi> 135. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litickly changed.</hi> 136</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Return of the Jews.</hi> 141</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roman Common-wealth.</hi> 21 <hi>Power.</hi> 89</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Royall Prieſt-hood.</hi> 160</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rule, the flagrant deſire of it.</hi> 7</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:106"/>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>SAmaria <hi>an imperiall ſeat</hi> 135</item>
               <item>Sameas. 101, 150</item>
               <item>Samuel. 97, 118</item>
               <item>Sanballets <hi>enterprize.</hi> 144</item>
               <item>Sanhedrin. 51, 78, 98</item>
               <item>Saul. 118</item>
               <item>Scaliger <hi>miſtaken.</hi> 102</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scepter of</hi> Juda. 64</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Schiſmaticall Jews.</hi> 65</item>
               <item>Scipio African. 132</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secrets to be admired.</hi> 159</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sedition brings ruin.</hi> 135</item>
               <item>Semiramis. 140</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Senators.</hi> 98, 126</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sepulchers.</hi> 54</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Servants releaſed.</hi> 16</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Servitude dwarfs the mind.</hi> 166</item>
               <item>Seſoſtris. 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seventh year.</hi> 26</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Shepheards active.</hi> 36</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:107"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Solemnity of Jubily.</hi> 16</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Soveraignty.</hi> 97</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>State, every ſtate breeds diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> 133</item>
               <item>Stolo <hi>violates his own Law.</hi> 18</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Subjection preferd before Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</hi> 116</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Succeſſoy.</hi> 118</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>TAlmud <hi>quoted.</hi> 14, 25, 48, 102, 154</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Temple, the voice there.</hi> 55 <hi>Only at</hi> Jeruſalem. 66</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Temple in</hi> Garizin 145</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ten tribes captive.</hi> 86, 137</item>
               <item>Theocracy. 6</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Territories enlarged.</hi> 57</item>
               <item>Tiberius. 166</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Times ordered.</hi> 111</item>
               <item>Titus. 167</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Trade.</hi> 28. <hi>Inherited.</hi> 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tranſlation of Nations.</hi> 137</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169754:107"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tribute heavy, an occaſion of rebellion.</hi> 131</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Truth before affection.</hi> 75</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V.</head>
               <item>VArro <hi>cited.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vertue loſt by want of exerciſe.</hi> 20</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Viciſsitude.</hi> 133</item>
               <item>Urim <hi>and</hi> Thummim. 51, 124</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVAr.</hi> 105</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wealth without op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion.</hi> 13</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>X.</head>
               <item>XEnophanes <hi>his ſaying.</hi> 158</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Y.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>YEar of reſt.</hi> 42. <hi>The ſixt years fruitfulneſs.</hi> 43</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Leap-year.</hi> 111</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Z.</head>
               <item>R. ZAcuth. 112, 129, 167</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
